music
music
The Central Research Institute's
The Central Research Institute's
nine-month knowledge review
nine-month knowledge review
speech will begin.
speech will begin.
Let's welcome Director Wang Yu
Let's welcome Director Wang Yu
to give us a round of applause.
to give us a round of applause.
applause
applause
Good evening, everyone.
Good evening, everyone.
Today, I think it's
Today, I think it's
Vice President Wang Fansheng came to host
王范生副院長來主持
he is also a historian
他也是歷史學家
So you can put this
所以可以把這個
It is also a good research partner with today's speaker
也跟今天的speaker是很好的研究夥伴
but today he is sick
不過今天他生病
So I'm here to introduce
所以有我來當介紹
but i want to have a
不過我想有一個
I'm the first to have the same sex with him
第一個我跟他同性
Second, I also care about history
第二個我也在乎歷史
So on this principle
所以就本著這個原則
Let me briefly introduce to you
我簡單跟大家介紹一下
our keynote speaker today
我們今天的主講人
Today's speaker is Academician Wang Mingke
今天主講人是王明科院士
Academician Wang Mingke graduated from
王明科院士是畢業於
Department of History, National Taiwan Normal University
臺灣師範大學歷史學系
Earn a Ph.D. from Harvard University
達到哈佛大學的博士學位
since 84
從84年開始
He has been in the Institute's History Research
他已經在本院的歷史研
language institute
語言研究所
In fact, the Institute of History
其實歷史研究所
The original research institute is also the largest and relatively old one in our institute.
原研究所也是本院最大的也是比較老的一個所
He used to teach in other than Academia Sinica
他曾經任教在除了在中研院之外
He also taught at National Taiwan University, Soochow University, Chung Hsing University
他也任教於台灣大學、東吳大學、中興大學
He was also transferred to Chung Hsing University as the Dean of Culture and Propaganda
也曾經介調過到中興大學擔任文宣院長
That was 2010 to 2013
那是2010到2013
In 2014, that is, last year, he was elected as a Third World Academician of the Institute of Election Research
2014年也就是去年當選中研院的第三世界院士
That's also currently a special review researcher at our Institute of History.
那也是目前還是我們歷史研究所的特評研究員
Dr. Wang from 94 to 2003
王博士在94到2003
I have been to western Sichuan many times, and there are three companies in Minjiang who have accumulated one-year experience
曾經多次到川西、敏江上有三間從事累積一年的
gun for field research
槍逐田野研究
From zero three to zero seven
零三到零七也到
Sichuan, Inner Mongolia, Xinjiang, Qinghai
四川內蒙、新疆、青海
Inspect the local environment
等地考察當地環境
The ecology of human beings with Youmu
與油木人類的生態
2007 to present
2007年到現在
His field research moved to
他的田野研究移到
Sichuan, Liangshan, etc.
四川、梁山等
minority autonomous regions
少數民族自治區
Tibetan
藏族
Yizu etc.
宜族等
The subject of study is history
研究的主題就是歷史
Multifaceted local
在本地的多元面向
and their living in human
以及他們在人類生活
The meaning of social development
社會發展的意義
so
所以
This is also very special
這個也很特別
So the number of people who signed up today is
所以今天報名的人數是
Far more than
遠超過
Over the years
歷年來的
If it is not enough to do, there is a TV broadcast outside
還不夠做的話外面是有電視的轉播
The results of Dr. Wang's field research on Jiangzhang ethnic minorities
王博士在藉著江漲族少數民族田野研究中所得的成果
It also illustrates the historical process of China and its fringe interdependence.
也在說明中國跟其邊緣相生相成的歷史過程
The results are also shown in a series of recent works
成果在最近一系列的著作裡面也表現出來
From 1997 published the edge of Huaxia
從1997年出版了華夏邊緣
2003 Guns between Han and Tibet
2003槍在漢藏之間
2006 is Heroes Ancestors and Brothers Democracy
2006是英雄祖先與弟兄民主
2009 is the nomad's choice
2009是遊牧者的抉擇
This year he published Reflection on History and Historiography Reflection
今年他出了反思史學與史學反思
If you are interested in this series of works
如果大家有興趣這一系列的著作
can be used as a reference
都可以做參考
Then I'll stop talking nonsense, please
那我廢話少說就請
Dr. Wang started his speech
王博士開始他的演講
I want to thank Dean Wang for introducing me.
我要謝謝這個王院長給我的介紹
I also want to thank the Central Plains Academy for giving me this opportunity
我也要謝謝中原院給我這個機會
name feasting on knowledge
用知識饗宴的名稱
to put some of my research
來把我的一些研究的一些
Some small thoughts to share with you
一些小小的心得跟大家分享
Since it's a feast
既然是饗宴
i think we all take it easy
我想我們大家都輕鬆一點
But today so many people came to this speech
不過今天這麼多人來聽這個演講
first i think
第一個我覺得
Maybe I got the title right
大概我這個題目就很正確
everybody really cares about history
大家都真的很在乎歷史
let's see
我們就看看
Actually what I'm going to talk about is
其實我這個要講的是
You know what history we care about
大家知道我們在乎的到底是什麼歷史
Because we knew from the beginning that people cared about history
因為我們一開始就知道大家很在乎歷史了
All right
好吧
Recently, everyone knows that in Taiwan some
最近大家都知道在台灣一些
Controversy over the History Curriculum of the State Religion
國教歷史課綱的爭議
There is also a grand commemoration of the 70th anniversary of the Anti-Japanese War in mainland China
還有中國大陸盛大的紀念這個抗戰70週年
international controversy
在國際間引起的爭議
Looks like it's all history's fault
看來都是歷史惹的禍
So what kind of history do we care about?
那我們在乎的到底是哪一種歷史呢
Is it a historical fact?
是歷史事實呢
Or how the historical facts should be written and presented
或者是歷史事實應該如何的書寫呈現
Or we really should be vested in history
或者我們真的是歷史應該被既得
strengthened
被強化
let everyone
讓人家都自
Let us all know the lessons of history
讓我們都知道歷史的教訓
or history should be forgotten
或者歷史應該被遺忘
Don't be a burden to contemporary people
不要成為當代人的包袱
That
那
I guess someone might say I don't care about history
我想可能有人說我不在乎歷史
Is it true that some people don't care about history?
那是不是真的有人不在乎歷史呢
i don't think so
我想不會
I'll tell you in a minute because we didn't
等一下我會跟大家講因為我們沒
Everyone lives in a world created by history
每一個人都活在歷史創造的世界裡面
At least some of you care about the history of the stock
至少大家有些人會在乎股票的歷史
The history of the company's earnings and its own adjustment history
公司收益的歷史跟自己的調新的歷史
and i think
還有我想
Many couples care about each other's social history before marriage
很多夫妻都很在乎對方婚前的社會史
so
所以
What is the history we care about?
被我們關懷的歷史到底是什麼呢
a very interesting phenomenon
一個非常很有趣的現象
It is the history in Chinese and the history in English
就是中文裡面的歷史和英文裡面的歷史
Both are one word with two meanings
都是一個詞有兩個意義
One meaning is those things that really happened in the past
一個意義是過去真正發生的那些事
there is another meaning
還有一個意義
It is people's memories, recollections and narratives of the past.
是人們對過去的記憶、回憶和敘述
In fact, these two are completely different things
其實這兩個是根本不一樣的事情
Why is it the same word in both English and Chinese?
為什麼在英文跟中文裡都是一個詞
In fact, there is a French scholar from all over the world, Portico
其實有一個法國全世界學者他Portico
have mentioned this
有提到這一點
He said that we people live in the real world created by history
他說我們人們是活在歷史造成的現實世界裡面
Is the cause of history
就是病因history
So we also write history in this world
所以我們也在這樣的世界裡面來書寫歷史
is making history
是making history
So we kind of mix those two things up
所以我們把這兩個事情好像混在一起了
so we think
所以我們就認為
Our historical facts and representations of historical memory
我們的歷史事實跟歷史記憶表述
Seems like they're all the same thing
好像都是同一回事一樣
so good
所以好
So let's talk about history that people care about
那我們來談談人們在乎的歷史
In fact, it is just the history I used to add the quartition mark
事實上實在只是我用加上quartition mark的歷史
To refer to people's memory and expression of the past
來指人們對過去的記憶跟表述
Because no matter how many real things that happened in the past
因為不管過去發生了多少真實的事情
No matter how accurately we reconstruct and state the facts of what happened in the past
無論我們如何的精確的去重建和陳述過去的發生事實
It's all about our choices about these facts
都涉及我們對於這些史實的選擇
and how do we express it
還有我們怎麼去表述它
Our expressions relate to our words
我們的表述涉及到我們的文詞
arrangement with law
與法的安排
These are deeply influenced by our society
這些呢都深深的受到我們的社會
and the influence of our individual situations in society
以及我們個人在社會裡面的一些處境的影響
So because of history and the social reality people live in and the identity of the individual during the period?
所以因為歷史和人們所處的社會現實和個人在期間的身份呢
closely related
密切相關
So simply speaking, we live in a society created by history.
所以簡單的講我們是活在歷史造成的社會裡面
especially living within the personal identities that history has created
特別是活在歷史所造成的個人的身份認同中
So it is difficult for us to recognize the influence of society on the construction of history
所以我們很難認識社會對歷史建構的影響
Even because of this, we don't really have a very good understanding of the social reality we live in.
甚至於我們因此對我們所處的社會現實都不是真正的非常了解
So I'm going to explain my arguments to you
所以我會跟大家解釋我這些論點
Then my method is a very special
那我的方法呢是一個很特別的
This is related to my research
這就是跟我的研究有關係
It is from a society that is very strange and strange to us
就是從一個對我們來講非常陌生奇特的社會
Get started with some history as locals believe
和當地的人所相信的一些歷史來著手
to show how they live in the history of their own making
來說明他們怎麼樣去活在他們自己創作的歷史
and related reality
和相關的現實裡面
How do they care about history and argue with others about history?
他們怎麼樣在裡面去在乎歷史和別人爭論歷史
that's what i said
這就是我說的
Walter is familiar with
華奇特為熟悉
This is what I spent more than ten years
這也是我花了十多年的時間
Research done on the Sichuan-Tibet Plateau
在川藏高原那邊所做的研究
But that's only half of my research
但是這只是我研究的一半
my other half
我另外的一半
is the logic i use like this
是我用這樣子的邏輯
Let's rethink the records in Chinese historical documents
來重新思考中國歷史文獻裡面的那些記載
So this means
所以這個就是說
I'm the same in this speech
在這個演講裡面我也是一樣
When I turn the stranger into the familiar
當我化陌生為熟悉之後
I want to explain what we are familiar with
我要說明我們所熟悉
The history of what you believe in and what you care about
所相信所在乎的歷史
peculiar in fact
事實上是奇特的
He was identified under a specific social situation
他是在一種特定的社會情境之下被鑒
They also reinforce a social situation like this
他們也強化這樣子的一個社會情境
This is Huashu Sivict
這個呢就是話書西維奇特
My example is the eastern edge of the Qinghai-Tibet Plateau
我的例子呢就是青藏高原東部的邊緣
Look at these three circles
大家看這三個圈圈
You can see that Chengdu is in this place
大家可以看到成都市在這個地方
This place is the Chengdu Plain
這個地方是成都平原
Its height is about 6,000 meters
它的高度大概是六千公尺
instead of around 600 meters
而不是六百公尺左右
what about this place
這個地方呢
This place is Songpan plateau here
這個地方是松潘高原在這裡
What about the plateau area here?
這邊的高原地區呢
about 3600 meters
大概是三千六百公尺
In other words, the drop is 3,000 meters
也就是說這個落差有三千公尺
so this place
所以這塊地方呢
Mountains and heavy lakes almost like steps
幾乎就像台階一樣的高山重湖
so what about this place
所以這個地方呢
This is caused by the extrusion of these two road blocks.
就是這兩個路塊擠壓造成的這種
Zhe District
哲區地區
So there is a very rich humanities here
所以這裡有非常豐富的人文
natural geographical landscape, plants
自然地理景觀、植物
It's the one over here and it's very rich
都是這邊的那個又非常豐富的
Then the gun bamboo I want to talk about first I want to introduce is here
那我要講的槍竹首先我要介紹的是在這裡
Then the Jiarong Zangzhu I introduced is here
然後我介紹的家榮藏竹在這裡
Here are two mountains and one bamboo
這裡是兩山一竹
so in this area
所以在這個地區呢
In fact, everyone should not think that these are three ethnic groups
事實上大家不要認為這是三個民族
In fact, before the ethnic surveys in mainland China identified and classified
事實上在中國大陸的民族調查識別分類之前
The people here are especially Tibetan bamboo and spear bamboo
這裡的人尤其是藏竹和槍竹
They all said that we have never heard of Tibetan bamboo
他們都說我們從來沒聽過什麼叫藏竹
never heard
聽都沒聽過
This is the name someone gave us
這是別人按給我們的名字
we have to accept
我們只好接受
So there are actually a lot of ethnic groups here
所以這邊其實是非常多的族群
people in every little valley
在每一個小山谷的人
He thinks he is a special group
他都認為自己是一個特別的族群
And it has nothing to do with the people around
而跟旁邊的人沒有什麼關係
So this is my field
所以這個是我的田野
My field is a multi-point field
我的田野採取的是一種多點田野
That is to say, this green
就是說這個綠色呢
is the field point representing me
是代表我的田野點
This is the same as the so-called squatting of many anthropologists
這跟很多人類學家的所謂的蹲點
At one point the ones that do it are not quite the same
在一個點上的那個做的是不太一樣
So my research on gun bamboo
所以我的關於槍竹的研究
The name of the book is Guns Between Han and Tibet
那本書名字叫做槍在漢藏之間
so you look at these two pictures
所以你看這兩張照片
you can see what's up with them
你就可以看得出來他們是怎麼回事
This is the spear bamboo in the east of Beichuan
這個是北川最東邊的槍竹
except me
我除外
was very young at that time
那個時候還很年輕
so you see all of them
所以你看他們所有的
Chairs made no matter what people wear
不管人家穿著做的椅子
if you can see clearly
如果你看得清楚的話
next to the house or something
旁邊的房子或什麼
It's exactly the same as Han bamboo
完全都是跟漢竹沒有兩樣
It is no different from Han bamboo in western Sichuan
跟川西的漢竹沒有兩樣
This place is the westernmost Xiaoxingou
這個地方是最西邊的小信溝
I do a lot of research here
我在這邊做研究做的很多
Gun bamboo here
這邊的槍竹
This is exactly the same as the Tibetan bamboo next to it
這就完全跟旁邊的藏竹沒有兩樣
So in the middle is a little bit of excessive past
所以中間就是一點一點的過度過去
so this is a
所以這是一個
So among the ethnic minorities in mainland China
所以在中國大陸的少數民族裡面
It is a very strange nation
它這是一個非常奇怪的一個民族
if we think of it as a nation
如果我們認為是一個民族的話
so you look at its environment
所以你看它的環境
Where they live is high mountains and deep valleys
他們住的地方是高山深谷
this is a ditch
這就是一條溝
It is a small tributary of the Min River
就是敏江的一條小支流
people
人呢
Look here is a village
看這邊有個村寨
This is Shanlonggou
這個是山龍溝
The location of this village is very high
這個村寨的位置非常的高
so when you get here
所以你到這裡的時候
you can't help but wonder
你就會不禁的想問
In other words, why do people live here?
就是說人為什麼要住在這裡
In fact, the simplest reason
其實最簡單的理由呢
just for safety
就是為了追求安全
pursue this
追求這個
see you later
等一下再來看
what about their lives here
他們在這邊的一些生活呢
They are plural to exploit a valley
他們是多元的利用一個山谷
vertical
垂直的
From this farm next to my home
從家旁邊的這個農田
To this place where wool cattle are raised on the mountain
到山上的這個養毛牛的這個場地
And then hunt the young ones will go out to hunt in the winter
然後打獵年輕人到冬天的時候會出去打獵
Everyone, look at this photo and you can see it again
大家看這張照片你又看出來
Their hairy cattle are almost like bison
他們的毛牛幾乎跟野牛一樣
Look here we brought a dog up here
你看這是我們帶了一條狗上去
So the leading bull comes to the dog
所以領頭的公牛就來對付這個狗
Then the young bulls count as a circle
然後年輕的公牛算是一個圈子
Keep the cow and calf behind
把母牛跟小牛保護在後面
This is the habit is exactly the same as that
這就是習性是完全跟那個
like the buffalo you saw in yerston
你在耶路斯棟看到的野牛一樣
this is their home
這個是他們家
This is Xiaoxingou Aiqi Village
這是小信溝愛奇村
farmland near their home
他們家附近的農田
This is their Jianjun mushroom on the mountain
這是他們的山上簡俊菇
Basically you occupy that little ditch
基本上這樣子你佔領那個小溝
Probably life without fish
大概生活就無魚了
But resources are very tight
但是資源非常的緊張
Every resource boundary here is very important
每一個在這邊資源界限非常的重要
so you see from this picture you can tell
所以你看從這張照片你可以看出來
Their tense relationship over this competition for resources
他們這個資源競爭的緊張的關係
This is the black tiger
這是這個黑虎在
That black tiger is here you see it's built on a ridge
那黑虎在你看它建在一個山脊上
There are very oblique fights on both sides
兩邊都是很斜的斗撲
Then this ridge was covered with some
然後這個山脊上還蓋了一些
Everyone looks like a chimney thing
大家看起來像煙囪樣的東西
that's not a chimney
那不是煙囪
That's a defensive tower
那個是防禦性的雕樓
So you look at Chinese literature
所以你在中國的文獻上你看
It is said that the black tiger gun was overturned in the Ming and Qing dynasties
說黑虎槍翻在明代跟清代的時候
is famously brutal
是有名的野蠻的
So wait a minute and I'll repeat
所以等一下我也會一再地
emphasize this to everyone
跟大家強調這一點
Documentation you have seen
你所看到的文獻記載
even the world you see
甚至你所看到的世界上
all other appearances
所有的其他的表面現象
it's all a representation
都是一個表象
What is the original image behind it?
那它背後的本象是什麼呢
as you can see in this picture
就像你在這張照片裡面所看到的
That is, the competition for resources is very fierce.
就是資源競爭非常激烈
People are in a very tense state
人在一個非常緊張的這種狀態裡面
This is Yonghegou, everyone sees it is the same
這是永和溝,大家看也是一樣
The houses are tightly packed together, on the hillside
房子緊緊的聚在一起,在山坡上
Min Jiang's Ziliu at the bottom is still at the bottom
底下的那個敏江的滋留還在很底下
It's also winter time and this farmland is dry
這也是冬天的時候,這個農田是乾的
This is Puxigou in Li County, you can see it more clearly
這個是李縣的普西溝,大家可以看得更清楚
This is a village, all the houses are tightly grouped together
這是一個村寨,都是房子緊緊的聚在一起
And it's far from the valley below
而且離底下的山谷還遠得很
It takes about 40 minutes to an hour to climb up.
這個爬上來都要大概四十分鐘到一個小時
Some villages take two hours to go up
有的寨子上去要兩個小時更高
This is where you see them, this is a black tiger
這是你看他們在,這個是冒陷的黑虎
Not that Oxtail Village
不是那個牛尾巴寨
During Chinese New Year, this is the beginning of the year and they have a ceremony
過年的時候,這是年初期他們有個儀式
inside a religious ceremony
在宗教儀式裡面
They're young and old with guns
他們年輕人跟壯年人都拿著槍
Shooting in the air, around a disused field next to the village
對空放槍,繞著村寨旁邊的一個廢掉的田
walk around
走一圈
In fact, they are all expressing
其實都是在表示
We are very determined to protect our Siyuan border
我們非常有決心來保護我們的思源邊界
This girl wears the same clothes
這女孩子穿的衣服也是一樣
now everyone will pay attention
在現在大家會注意
Everywhere these girls dress alike
每一個地方的這些女孩子穿著相似的
then just say
然後就說
This is the national costume tradition of our gun clan
這個就是我們槍族的民族服飾傳統
But for the locals
但是對當地人來講
That's not it, similarity doesn't matter
那個不是,相似不重要
The important thing is the difference between his clothing and that of the village next to him
重要的是他跟旁邊的村寨的穿著上的區分
Even a small distinction is very important to them
即使是一點點的區分對他們來講都非常重要
because in this place
因為在這個地方
Resource competition and differentiation are important
資源競爭跟區分是重要的
so this is
所以這個就是
back to my field work
又回到我做田野的
Xiaoxinge Aiqi Village, where I live the most
我在這邊住的最多的小信哥愛奇村
You see, this village is different from the one before
大家看這個村子跟前面不一樣
it is scattered
它是分散的
i know them well
我跟他們很熟
so i joke with them sometimes
所以我有時候就跟他們開玩笑
once i said
有一次我說
You are so small, why did your house fall apart?
你小不小的你們的房子為什麼是散了
not get together like you
不跟你一樣聚在一起
they said yes
他們說對啊
we never noticed this
我們從來沒注意到這一點
make sense
你講個道理看看
I said because you are robbing people
我說因為你們是搶人的
you were not robbed
你們不是被搶的
They used to be very upstream
他們以前是非常上游的
famous savage
有名的蠻子
Local within an identity system
當地在一種認同體系裡面
very interesting
非常有意思的
people from every region
每一個地區的人
In fact, what I call a region is not a very big one.
其實我所謂的地區不是非常大一地區
It's just a small ditch or a section of a small ditch.
就是一個小溝或者一個小溝裡面的一段而已
The people over there may be just a few children
那邊的人可能就是幾個在子而已
They call themselves Erma
他們就自稱自己叫Erma
People in the upper reaches are called barbarians
就稱上游的人都是叫蠻子
Then the people downstream are those cunning Han Chinese
然後下游的人都是那些狡猾的漢人
But the people from that village called Manzi
但是被稱為蠻子的那個村寨的人
He also calls himself a horse
他也自稱自己是兒馬
Then he called the people below are Han Chinese
那他就稱底下的是漢人
On the contrary, you think others are barbarians
反而你認為別人是蠻子
Others think you are Han Chinese
別人認為你是漢人
He thinks the barbarian is on the root
他認為蠻子在根上面
So this is a situation of ethnic identity in the local area
所以這就當地的以前的一種族群認同的狀況
So it's New Year's Eve
所以這個是過年的時候
their wedding ceremony
他們的結婚的儀式
This is also Xiaoxingou Aiqi Village
這個也是小信溝愛齊村
it's winter
這是冬天
outside their house
他們的這個屋子外面
Pile up a lot of firewood
堆了很多的柴火
inside the house
屋子裡面
There are some pig signs hanging on the roof beams
屋樑上掛了一些豬標
for them
對他們來講
This is the greatest safety in life
這個就是生活最大的安全
Maximum protection
最大的保障
So we take a look at the history of what they believe
所以我們來看看他們相信的歷史
This is what the people in the ditch in Egypt said
這個是從埃及溝的民眾他們所講的
This is what I use to record and divide it into text
這個我都是用錄音然後把它劃成文本
He said that the first time there was no one
他說最早沒有人的時候
three brothers big brother is a woman
三個兄弟大哥是一個婆子
brother here
兄弟到這兒來了
Another one invited a brother to the Iraqi team
還有一個邀兄弟到伊隊去了
My brother said that I can bask in the sun when I live here
大哥說我住在這兒可以曬太陽
So the sun shines early for the three teams
所以三隊太陽曬得早
invite brother a little scared
邀弟有些怕
The second brother said that if you die, you will be buried in my second team.
二哥就說那你死了就埋到我二隊來
So a team of dead people are brought here to be buried
所以一隊的人死了都抬到這兒來埋
it's such a simple history
這這麼簡單一個歷史
that means the people of this place
就說明這個地方的人
The relationship between the three in sub
三個在子之間的關係
Also this is what another guy told me
另外這是另外一個人跟我講的
He said that the seven brothers from the top
他說高頭來的七個弟兄
Some of the seven brothers are in the big ear
那個七個弟兄有些在大耳邊
some in pigs ears
有些在豬耳邊
That's how those wolves fucked your dad
那些狼乾你爸是這樣子分出來的
they are here
他們是在這兒
What dynasty was fanned
啥子朝代被打扇的
run here
跑到這兒來
It turns out that there is no one here
原來這個沒有人
Here are the seven brothers
這下子七個兄弟來
You see he later said only three brothers came
你看他後來說只來了三個兄弟
Four more brothers are out there
還有四個兄弟是在外面
The seven big ears Niba
那七大耳邊尼巴
This is how people are divided
人是這樣分出來的
So this one is different from the one just now
所以這個跟剛才那個不一樣
story told
講的故事
That is to say, the three brothers
就是說這個三個兄弟
It turned out to be three of the seven brothers
原來是七個兄弟裡面的三個
This is another record
這也是另外一個記錄
This man also told me
這個人也是跟我講
he became nine
他就變成了九個
He said nine brothers came
他說來了九個兄弟
nine brothers stand there
九個兄弟站在那地方
Three brothers started a fire in this ditch
三兄弟打火在這條溝
two brothers over there
兩個兄弟在那邊
So there's an interesting dictation from him later on.
所以後面有一段他的口述很有意思
i read it out
我把它唸出來
He said the nine brothers were Huang Cao
他說九兄弟是黃曹
he ask me
他問我
Qin Dynasty or Huang Cao
秦朝還是黃曹
Qin Dynasty three people eight million
秦朝三人八百萬
Huang Cao three people eight million
黃曹三人八百萬
I said whatever
我說隨便
he can't escape
他就躲不脫
here it is
就到這兒來了
A family of little brothers came here
一家小兄弟就到這兒來了
We know that Qin Dynasty and Huang Cao
我們知道那個秦朝跟黃曹
one is the people
一個是人民
And the times are far behind
而且時代差了很遠
What does this mean?
這代表什麼意思?
That time means nothing to them.
那個時間對他們來講一點意義都沒有
Their history is a past combined with the present
他們的歷史就是一個過去跟現在結合在一起
In the past few brothers came here
過去幾個兄弟到這裡來
what are we now
我們現在是什麼?
This is a very special kind of history
這是一個非常特別的一種歷史
so everyone see
所以大家看
I can simplify the first few to this
我可以把前面幾個簡化成這樣子
if you want to explain this side
如果你要解釋這邊
The origin of the three Zai Ziren
三個在子人的來路
You said once upon a time three brothers came here
你說從前有三個兄弟到這裡來
then go to a place alone
然後一個人到一個地方
And then you have to explain where this large range of people comes from?
然後你要解釋這個大範圍的人從哪裡來的呢?
You say that once upon a time seven brothers came here
你就說從前有七個兄弟到這裡來
Then what about everyone?
然後大家怎麼樣?
stand alone in one place
一個人站一個地方
and then a wider range
然後更大範圍
This is if you go to Jiuzhaigou to play
這個是如果大家到九寨溝去玩的話
take off when the plane lands
飛機降落的時候起飛
did you see a big mountain
你有看到一個大山
That's called Snowberg Peak
那個叫雪堡頂山
If you ask him, he said that the top mountain of Snow Castle
如果你問他說拜雪堡頂山
that plugged in
那個堵入
Where did all the people come from?
所有的人是從哪裡來的?
He will tell you another
他就告訴你另外一個
seven brothers story
七兄弟的故事
That is to say, how can these people believe
就是說你說這些人怎麼會相信
Such a strange history, right?
這麼奇怪的歷史對不對
ok i tell you
好 我告訴你
to tell everyone is to say
告訴大家就是說
Why do they believe this history
他們為什麼相信這個歷史
Egyptian village has three children
埃及村有三個在子
one pair two pair three pair
一對二對三對
There are more than fifty households
共有五十多戶人
just a small child
就是很小一個在子
One-to-two couples in Yingsan-myeon
一對二對在英山面
That's what I just said
就是剛才講的說那個
Who said he was a little scared when he died?
誰說他死了有點怕
He said his brother said
他說他哥哥就說
Then you die and bury me here
那你死了就埋到我這裡來
In fact, the reaction is that these two sons
其實反應就是這兩個在子
close relationship
關係比較密切
Three pairs in Yangshan-myeon
三對在陽山面
Yangshan noodles usually we say
陽山面通常我們就講
This is what the sun shines early in the morning
這個是太陽一大早就照得到的
So production is better
所以生產比較好
Usually more people
通常人比較多
so they just
所以他們就
the story just now
剛才那個故事
History says that he was the big brother
歷史裡面就說那是大哥
admit he's the big brother
承認他是大哥
But it's a bit derogatory to him
但是又有點貶義他
Said big brother because it is a neck
說大哥因為是一個脖子
so we let him
所以我們讓他
so in this place
所以在這個地方
The homes and houses of coal households are all located on the foundation of a specific land god
煤戶的家子、屋子都坐落在特定地盤神的地基上
The name of the land god is also the name of the family
地盤神的名字也是家族的名字
and very consciously
而且非常有意識的是
No land God can't build a house
沒有地盤神不能蓋房子
So what is the effect of everyone being so smart?
所以大家這樣智慧造成一個什麼效果
in this ravine
在這個山溝裡面
If there are 30 households, there will always be 30 households
如果有30戶就永遠30戶
Forever 50 households
永遠50戶
If there are 50 land gods, there will always be 50 households
如果是50個地盤神就永遠50戶
Another effect is
還有一個效果就是
I'm for relatives, it's actually a spatial relationship
我為了親戚關係其實是空間關係
Because if you move to another
因為你如果搬到另外一個
For example, a place is vacant
譬如說有一個地方地盤空下來了
There is a father who has many sons
有一個父親他的兒子多
He can't help living at home is difficult
他沒辦法家裡面生活困難
He can get the consent of other people in Murakami
他可以取得村上其他人的同意
Said my son was going to take that place
說我兒子去佔那個地盤
build a house over there
在那邊蓋房子
If everyone in the village agrees
如果村上人都同意的話
Then his son will set up a household there
那麼他兒子就在那邊成立一戶
Then the father and the son will become
然後這個父親跟這個兒子就會變成
into a different family
變成不同家族的
because of that son
因為那個兒子
he is the inherited family
他是承受的那個家族
The wound of the land god
地盤神的傷
so think about it
所以大家想想看
What does it mean to live in the historical construction
什麼叫做活在歷史建構的
In social reality
社會現實裡面
That is to say, today a person of the second race
就是說今天一個二族的人
he went hunting
他去打獵
he chased a camphor
他追一個樟子
one way
一條一種路
When chasing to the edge of the clan's territory
追到一族的地盤邊緣的時候
he stopped suddenly
他突然就止步了
in his heart
他心裡面的
because that history told him
因為那個歷史告訴他
This is not the land of our ancestors
這個不是我們祖先的地盤
And their ancestors were brothers to mine
而且他們的祖先跟我的祖先是弟兄
so if today i
所以我如果今天
words that cross the line
越界的話
it will break the brotherhood
會壞了兄弟感情
so he stopped
所以他就止步了
so think about it
所以大家想想看
people live in this history
人活在這個歷史裡面
Your actions and actions all prove this history
你的依舉、依動都證明這個歷史
so maybe this time
所以也許這個時候
another one
另外一個
people of that clan
那個一族的人
Will watch super super super
會超超地在旁邊觀察
not crossing the line
沒有越界
Then he sees you cross the line
然後他一看你們越界
good
好
You are still my good brother
居然你還是我的好兄弟
What if at this time
如果這個時候呢
They heard a whistling in the distance
他們聽到遠方有一聲呼嘯
he knows
他知道呢
there is a side
是有旁邊的
people with big ear ditches maybe
也許大耳邊溝的人
come over here to hunt frog waist
過來我們這邊打獵蛙腰
and then everyone
然後所有的人呢
I have to go there to drive people away
都要過去把人家趕走
why
為什麼呢
because history tells them
因為歷史告訴他們
Our ancestors were three brothers
我們的祖先是三個兄弟
brothers are cooperative
兄弟是合作的
so what
所以呢
Cooperation distinguishes confrontation
合作區分對抗
in this history
是這個歷史裡面
a very important narrative symbol
非常主要的一個敘事符號
is brother
就是弟兄
his three metaphors
他的三種隱喻
it's brother
就是兄弟呢
is cooperative
是合作的
Because brothers are born of the same father
因為兄弟是同一個父親生的
and what about brother
然後兄弟呢
It's another brother's name
又是親兄弟名算帳
Brothers of all kinds
兄弟各式各的
and brother
還有兄弟呢
There will always be some small contradictions
永遠是有一些小的矛盾
forever in this little struggle
永遠在這個小小的鬥爭裡面
So people live in historically constructed
所以人們活在歷史建構的
this social phenomenon
這個社會現象
And then the social reality is so real
然後社會現實又是如此的真實
Because every action of yours is confirming this history
因為你的每一個行動都在印證這個歷史
People naturally believe and care about this history
人們自然也相信 也在乎這個歷史
So in this place apart from the history
所以在這個地方除了歷史以外
wait a minute if you have time you can talk
等一下如果有時間的話可以講
their Trinity disc belief
他們的三神地盤形信仰
all guide and tell them what to do
都指引了告訴他們應該怎麼做
A person's actions follow these
一個人的行動都是跟著這些
What we call history and culture and religion
我們所謂的歷史跟文化和宗教
So this history is actually the same as our history
所以這個歷史裡面其實跟我們的歷史裡面
seems to have a lot of details
好像有很多的細節
There are also some small details in their history.
他們的歷史裡面也有一些小小的細節
These details also differentiate this group of people
這些細節也把這個人群做一些區分
This detail is sometimes too simple to tell.
這個細節有時候講起來也是太簡單了
It is often said that when the three brothers separated
常常就講說三個兄弟在分家的時候
they kill a cow
他們殺一頭牛
One for the head, one for the tail and one for the body
一個分到牛頭 一個分到牛尾巴 一個分到牛身子
or when three brothers separated
或者三個兄弟分家的時候
One to one who seems like they say metal
一個分到一個好像他們說金屬做的人吧
a man made of gold
一個分到是金子做的人
One is the silver man
一個分的是銀人
Iron Man
一個分的是鐵人
and then something like this
然後就是這樣子的
it's that simple
就是這麼簡單
So they usually yell and yell
所以他們平常就會罵來罵去
Like the Yonghegou side
像永和溝這邊就是說
Who is the descendant of Niu Pizi?
說誰是牛皮子的後代
who is the offspring of oxtail
誰是牛尾巴的後代
Of course, a cowhide oxtail
當然一聽牛皮子牛尾巴
it must be a comparison
就一定是比較
The relatively weaker this, this, and this Zaizi
比較勢力比較弱的這個這個在子
What about Beichuan Inner and Outer Ditch?
北川內外溝呢
This place is more Chinese
這個地方是比較漢化的
So you see they have Chinese surnames
所以你看他們就有了漢姓
Zhang exiled three surnames to Xiaoba
張流亡三姓人到小霸來
come three brothers
過來三兄弟
So it is impossible for the three brothers to intermarry
所以三兄弟不可能通婚
So I changed my last name
所以改了姓
Then they said that a person stood in a ditch
然後他們就說一個人站了一條溝
One is Sanshulin
一個是三樹林
That's Liu's
那是劉家
The other is the inner and outer grooves
另一個是內外溝
It was a farm
當時是農家
In fact, there is a big controversy
其實一個爭議比較大
Now say it's Wang's
現在說是王家
So some oral histories like this
所以像這樣子的一些口述歷史的呢
Actually very inspiring to me
其實對我都非常有啟發
Indicates that history is often changed in such disputes
表示歷史常常在這種爭議中被改變
So the belief in the three gods in the ditch of Egypt is the same
所以埃及溝的三神信仰也是一樣
Each of the three carriers has its own territory
三個載子各有各的地盤
So they banded together to protect their common turf
所以他們聯合起來保護共同的地盤
So the three gods are also used to emphasize this kind of human ecology
所以三神也用來強調這樣子的人類生態
Simply put, each carrier has its own three gods
簡單來講每一個載子都有自己的三神
Then combine if the three carriers have a groove
然後聯合起來如果三個載子具有一條溝的話
The three of them together have a bigger three gods
他們三個合起來上面又有一個更大的三神
So the biggest three gods in this place are Coronado
所以在這個地方最大的三神就是哥羅納厝
This is the symbol of the three gods
三神的標誌就是這樣子
a sign on the hill
在山上一個標誌
So when I run up the hills with these friends who live with guns
所以當我跟著這些槍住的朋友在山上跑的時候
When you come across a sign like this
碰到了這樣子的標誌的時候
we're going to walk around
我們就要在附近的走
less numbers plugged in to show worship
少一些數字插上去表示敬拜
This means that
這個意思也代表就是說
I respect other people's territory boundaries
我尊重別人的地盤界限
The location of the three gods is usually the boundary of the territory
三神的位置通常也就是地盤界限
ok let's see now
好 我們現在來看
Jialong Tibetan
這邊佳龍藏族
what they call history
他們所說的歷史
So let me briefly introduce
所以我簡單的介紹一下
Everyone knows the location
大家看那個地理位置就知道
its environment of production
它的環境生產方式
Very similar to the neighbor's gun family
和邻居的槍族非常相似
It also has a similar tritheistic belief
它也有類似的三神信仰
That is to say, it is the same here
也就是說在這邊也是一樣
that is
就是
As long as there is faith in the three gods
只要有三神信仰
Everyone pays great attention to the land
大家就非常注重地盤
Then also have this
然後也是同樣的有這個
No house can be built where there is no site god
沒有地盤神的地方就不能蓋房子
this custom
這種習俗
But in the homes of ordinary people here
但是在這邊一般老百姓的家裡
I can not find
我找不到
I can't interview people like this
採訪不到這種像類似的
History of the Dixiong's Ancestors
地雄祖先的歷史
Then this kind of history only exists in the beliefs of the various Tushi families in the past
那這種歷史只存在於過去各土石家族的信仰裡面
Sorry, I'm here to explain to you
抱歉 在這裡我要跟大家說明一下
I forgot to say first
剛才我忘了先說
In fact, the situation I am talking about
其實我現在講的這種情形
mostly before the 1950s
大部分是在1950年代以前
At most, this situation lasted until 1960 and 70
最多這種情形延續到1960、70
Later, because after the so-called liberation of mainland China
後來因為在中國大陸所謂的解放以後
there is a big change
就有很大的變化
So this is what it used to be
所以這個都是以前的情形
In the past, this place was governed by various chieftains
那過去這個地方是由各個土司管轄的
They all usually refer to people from all over the world by the name of Tusi
他們都通常以土司的名字來稱各地的人
Such as this Badi, Bawang, Zaku, Droth family
如這個巴底人、巴旺人、渣古人、卓斯家人
Then each chieftain led probably a dozen to dozens of villages
那每一個土司他所率領的大概是十幾個到數十個村寨
and very important
還有非常重要的
They are different from Gunru
他們跟槍儒那邊不一樣的
they are very religious
他們是非常虔誠的
Followers of Tibetan Buddhism
藏傳佛教的信徒
You see, the river next to it is the Dadu River
大家看,旁邊的河就是大渡河
this is a village
這是一個村寨
This village came out of this ravine
這個村寨就在這條山溝裡面沖出來的
This little bit of alluvial soil is filled and cultivated here
這一點點的填衝擊土裡面在這邊耕作
So the location of this village
所以這個村寨的位置
it's about the place
這個跟地方有關
This is not the same as the gun bamboo
這個跟槍竹那邊不太一樣
Qiangzhu would never dare to build a village so close to the river
槍竹是絕對不敢把村寨蓋在這麼靠河邊的地方
On the one hand, I am afraid of flooding, on the other hand, I am also afraid of being forced
一方面怕氾濫,一方面也怕被勉強
This is the village of Merlo
這個是墨爾洛村
This is one of my field points
這是我的一個田野點
Wait a minute, everyone can see
等一下大家可以看
this is also a
這個也是一個
The house and the form of the settlement are also a sign
這個房子跟聚落形態也是一種表徵
wait a minute you look at this and that
等一下你看這個跟那個
Wait a minute I'm showing you this
等一下我給大家看的這個
The House of Liang Fan Yi Family
梁餐宜族的房子會
very different
非常的不一樣
Simply put, you can see that this house is very delicate
簡單講你可以看到這個房子非常的精緻
Because its house is built on the site rope
因為它房子蓋在地盤繩的地方
So once you cover it and live there, it will last a long time.
所以一蓋下去一住下來就非常的久
not easy to move
不太容易搬走
So their house is very particular
所以他們那個房子非常的講究
This is also the year when I went to take pictures for their wedding
這也是有一年過年我去替他們結婚了拍照
so this kind of wedding
所以這種婚禮
This is called Qilu Village
叫這個是齊魯村的
Go to Morle Village and bring this girl back
到莫爾樂村把這個女孩子接回來
This kind of wedding is where the whole village attends
這種婚禮就是全村都參加
The whole village will stay in Moerle Village for one night
就全村到莫爾樂村住一晚上
The next day the girl bid farewell to the elder
第二天這個女孩子就拜別長老
Then go to her husband's village
然後就到她的夫家的村落去
So this place is also famous as the Valley of Beauty
所以這個地方也是有名的這個美人谷
Look at this, it's really beautiful
大家看這個真的是很漂亮
But this actually shows another
但是這個其實也表現了另外一個
Phenomena unrelated to my research
跟我的研究無關的現象
I just told you
我剛才跟大家說
Diversity can be found here in every discipline
每一個學科都可以在這邊發現多樣性
This is one of the genetic diversity
這個是基因多樣性的之一
That is to say, some genes happen to be concentrated in this place
就是說正好某一些基因就集中在這個地方
Let me tell you this village is called Badi Village
這個告訴你們這個村叫做這個巴底村
There are more than a dozen villages here in Badi
這個巴底這邊有十幾個村子
people are beautiful
人都很漂亮
There is also a Meinan Valley
另外還有一個美南谷
If you are interested, you can ask me
有興趣可以問我
It's even weirder if you look at the history here.
你看這邊的歷史就更奇怪了
But this history is from the 1930s to the turn of the 40s when
但是這個歷史是1930年代到40年代之交的時候
An early anthropologist Mr. Ma Changshou
一個早期的人類學家馬長壽先生
he is collected
他是採集的
He said that the lion of the barren valley has a giant bird to meet the poor
他說荒谷獅之士有巨鳥約窮者
born in poor cloth
降生在窮布
This is the name of the virtue of poor cloth
窮布之德名有此
He is called Lord of the Poor Birds
他就叫做窮鳥之主
the bird laid five eggs
生了那個鳥生了五個蛋
One red one green one white one black one flower
一紅一綠一白一黑一花
A person came out of the flower egg
花蛋裡面出來一個人
Bear hand life, eye descendants
熊手人生 眼神子孫
Taining
牽到太寧
This Taining is Bamei
這個太寧是八美
just when he was near a
就是在他臨近一個
A small center of a Tibetan Buddhist
一個小的一個藏傳佛教的中心
lead to the bottom
又牽到八底
Then on the eight bottom side
然後在八底這邊
He gave birth to two brothers
他生了兄弟兩個人
It's just these two people who will become apprentices with all kinds of prosperity
就是這兩個人就變成八底八旺的徒師
take a look
大家看看
There is an extra symbol of this poor bird on it
上面多了這個窮鳥的符號
right
對不對
This is what is said in Tibetan Buddhism
這是一個藏傳佛教裡面所講的
a garuda
一個Garuda
Garuda
就是金翅大棚鳥
Read this story below
底下大家看這個故事
still a brother story at the end
到最後還是一個兄弟故事
use a brother story
用個兄弟故事
To show the ancestral relationship of the two apprentices
來表現這個兩個徒師的祖先關係
This is also collected by Mr. Ma Changshou
這個也是馬長壽先生採集的
Ge Se Zhan Tushi's ancestors in his family
格色展徒師的他家裡面的祖元
He said that our ancestors were brought from the poor Ministry of 39
他說我們的祖先是從39部的窮部牽來
The poor actually refers to
窮部其實是指
Just like Lhasa
就是拉薩那樣
He said that this has been here for three, four or five generations.
他说这个是来这边已经有三四五代
When I came here, there were four brothers
来的时候有兄弟四个人
You see the same poor bird symbol
你看同样的有穷鸟的符号
Then there are four brothers
然后后面又是四个兄弟
another brother story
又是一个弟兄故事
So this is the ancestor of another Zhuoshijia toast
所以这是另外一个卓士甲吐司的祖先
also the same
也是一样
Every one of these toasts tells a story about their ancestors
每一个这种吐司讲他们的祖先故事
It's all like a pattern
都是好像有个模式一样的
follow this pattern
都是顺着这个模式
so why do they care about history like this
所以他们为什么在乎这样的历史
very simple
很简单
It's the toast family
就是吐司家族
their divinity and ruling authority
他们的神性和统治威权
It is from this history
就是来自于这样的历史
In addition, the relationship between the toast and the adjacent toast
另外吐司和临近家吐司之间的关系
It is shown in the brother's story below
就表现在底下那个弟兄故事上面
he thinks more
他越认为
The more he thinks that toast and I are brothers
他越认为那个吐司跟我是弟兄
means
就表示
friend and foe
又是朋友又是敵人
It's the closer the relationship
就是這種關係越最親近
The most I do in the field is to look at the bottom and the bottom
我做田野做的最多的是在八底八望
These two places are
這兩個地方就是
that's what the relationship is like
那個關係就是這樣子
And the language of the two places is completely different
而且兩個地方是語言完全不同
They know each other's language is full of curse words
他們會對方的語言都是罵人的話
They've heard each other talk since they were kids
他們就從小就聽到對方講什麼
He came back and asked his parents
他就回來問他父母說
The people on the other side of the river called me or something
河那邊的人罵我什麼什麼的
what is that
那個是什麼
So all he learns is swearing
所以他學的都是罵人的話
so there is
所以還有
It is the core area of local Tibetan Buddhism
它是本地藏傳佛教的核心地區
It native and Tibetan Buddha
它本地和藏傳佛
It is to admit that one is a Tibetan Buddhist
就是承認自己是藏傳佛教裡面
we are the edge
我們是邊緣
all core
全部是核心
So I also collected here
所以我在這邊還採集到了
very interesting
非常有意思的
There is a special family called the Vastus
有一個特別的一個家族叫瓦斯土斯
At the exact epicenter of the 2008 Great Western Sichuan Earthquake
在2008年的那個川西大地震的正好震央
right here
就在這個地方
I have collected and seen three versions here
我在這邊採集到看到三種版本
Three brothers in the same family
同一個家庭裡面三個兄弟
Actually told the history of three different pairs of families
居然講了三個不同的對家族的歷史
The first one is what the family tree of Tusi said
第一個這是土司的家譜所講的
It's mainly about one of their ancestors
講的主要是一個他們的祖先
be a hero
是一個英雄
From Ushizang is from Lhasa
從烏士藏就是從拉薩那邊過來的
Then come to replace China's poverty
然後來替中國貧亂
So China gave him Xuanwei envoy
所以中國就給他宣衛使應
Then just manage the natives here
然後就在這邊管這邊的土著
The story is that the chieftain's younger brother
這個故事是這個土司的弟弟
Usually the chieftain's younger brother is the main local lama
通常土司的弟弟就是當地最主要的喇嘛
This lama told the story of their family
這個喇嘛講了他們家族的故事
You see, it's the same as the previous one again
你看又是跟前面那個一樣
The big bird in the sky laid a few more eggs
天上大捧鳥又生了幾個蛋
Then how does this egg go?
然後這個蛋怎麼樣怎麼樣到哪裡
which toast
變成哪幾個土司
This is another brother of a chieftain
這是一個土司的另外一個弟弟
This brother, he talked about it again and again.
這個弟弟他講了又講了一個
It is said that Henan people have a Three Kingdoms
說河南人有個三國泰
what brought four people
什麼帶了四個人
A son immigrated to Sichuan
一個兒子到四川做移民
one to one
一個到貫獻
One to Jintang Peng Xian generation
一個到金堂彭憲一代
there is one more here
還有一個呢到這裡
there's one more back
那還有一個回到
Returning to Yuanji means returning to Henan
回到元吉就是回到河南去了
So you see this becomes a bro story again
所以你看這個又變成一個弟兄故事
right
對不對
what's going on
那是怎麼回事呢
Actually
其實呢
Because of this I feel that this history
因為這個我覺得這個歷史
really very strange
真的是非常奇怪
that's what i'm talking about
就是我講的這種
they happen to be caught in
他們正好是夾在
Between the two forces of Han and Tibetan
漢藏兩個勢力的中間
So he is in the same family
所以他這個同一個家裡面
Where are the three brothers?
三個兄弟呢
They care about different histories
他們在乎的歷史都不一樣
that big brother is toast
那個大哥是吐司
Of course he cares about the first version
他當然在乎第一個版本的
Because that can prove his identity as a toast
因為那個能夠證明他吐司的身份
right
對不對
The second brother is a lama
二哥呢是一個喇嘛
He believes in the kind of divinity
他比較相信那種神性的那種
he and each toast
他跟各個吐司
family relationship
家族之間的關係
this old
這個老
where is this toast
這個吐司呢
He's talking about a local culture
他講的就是本地的一種文化
special culture
特別的文化
How do you think about history?
就是怎麼去想歷史呢
all brothers
都是幾個兄弟
At first it was a few brothers
開始都是幾個兄弟
good
好
Finally, I want to talk about this Liangshan survivor
最後我要講到這個梁山遺族
look
你看
His population is different from before
他的人口就跟前面不一樣
Of course, the Liangshan area is relatively large
當然以梁山地區是比較大
bigger than the previous ones
比前面那些地區大
But more people
但是人口多多了
23.06 million
2306萬
In addition to the Jiaotong University basin,
那這邊除了有交大的盆地以外
His environment is similar to that of the Sichuan-Tibetan Qiang people
他的環境跟川西藏腔族差不多
He is a part-time farmer and logger
他農木兼營
These are similar to the Tibetan accent
這些也跟藏腔族差不多
But the biggest difference is his sociality
但最大的差別就是他的社會性
his this
他的這個
he
他
Let me just say it here
我這邊先簡單的講
He doesn't have the belief in the three gods of the Tibetan people
他沒有藏腔族的三神信仰
But he has a wealth of skill combined with blood
但是他有豐富的加之血緣技藝
This is something Tibetans don't have
這個是藏腔族沒有的
So everyone, think about Tibetan accents
所以大家想想看藏腔族的
the kind of history we just talked about
剛才我們所講的那種歷史
There is only one past combined with the present
只有一個過去跟現在結合在一起
if the family history
如果說家庭的歷史
Almost only three generations at most
幾乎最多只記得三代
I don't remember any further
再往前面就不記得了
Then the structure of their house is very simple
然後他們的房屋這邊構造非常的簡單
And do not pay attention to the site
而且不注重地盤
They don't even like to build houses on old machines
他們甚至蓋房子不喜歡蓋在老地機上
They love to move around
他們很喜歡搬家到處搬遷
and very important
還有非常重要的
He has rulers and ruled
他是有統治者跟被統治者
A Consecutive Total Information Society
區分的一種接續化的總信社會
So of course this is over
所以這個當然是過去了
But his traces are still there
但是他的遺痕到現在還在
They are divided into rulers are black chairs
他們這分為統治者是黑椅
The white chair is the subordinate farmer
白椅是隸屬的農人
Then there are two other classes behind are slaves
然後另外後面還有兩個階級的都是奴隸
Both the black chair and the white chair have family property
黑椅、白椅他們都有家資
Everyone belongs to his family property
每一個人都屬於他的家資
Concentration of black chair family property residence
黑椅家資居住的集中
The white chair family property is because of him
白椅家資因為他
it belongs to each black chair
它分属于各个黑椅
so they are difficult to unite
所以它们很难团结
this is how it used to be
这是过去的情形
look at this house
大家看这个房子
this house is abandoned
这个房子是被废弃的
So their houses are built very simply
所以它们房子盖得很简单
If you want to move, just throw it away.
要搬家就把它丢了就是了
Look here and that too
你看这边那也是
this is the house over there
这是那边的房子
the village
村落
in this village
在这个村落里面
everywhere you can see
到处你都可以看到
These formerly abandoned houses
这些以前被废弃的房子
Because they don't like building on old foundations
因为它们不喜欢在老地基上盖房子
This may also be obsolete
这个可能也是被废弃的
This is where people live
这个就是有人住
The house is very
这个房子都是非常的
compared to the front
比起前面来看
very simple
非常的简陋
These two are white chairs
这两个位是白椅
this is the black chair
这位是黑椅
this is his grandmother
这个是他祖母
let's visit him
我们来访问他
Then
然后
I tell a few stories about this little boy
我讲几个这个小孩子的故事
that
那个
This kind of historical memory in their home can best illustrate
最能夠說明他們的這個家之的這種歷史記憶
this kind of
這一類的
Because when he took me around to visit
因為他帶著我到處去訪問的時候
Often I hear someone ask him
常常我就聽到有人問他說
Are you the kid who burned down the house?
你是不是把人家屋子燒掉那個小孩
I listened to it a few times and came back one night when we were chatting
我聽了幾次以後有一次晚上回來沒事我們聊天的時候
I'll just say what great things you did as a kid
我就說你小時候做過什麼偉大的事情
people remember you
人家都記得你
he was very embarrassed
他就很不好意思
Said I was playing with fire in the back of the house once when my dad called me
說我有一次在我爸爸罵我我在屋子後面玩火
Burn the whole village in half
就把整個村子燒掉一半
Say this, this, this, his father, this
說這個這個這個他他爸爸呢把這個
The sheep are all sold and there is nothing to do with them
羊都賣了陪人家還還沒辦法
So let's take him and everyone to think about this scene that looks very touching.
所以就帶著他大家想想看看起來很感人的這個場面
A father with a six-year-old child
一個一個父親帶著一個六歲的小孩
Mountains everywhere in Liangshan Prefecture began to be called home
整個梁山州到處的山上去開始被家之
Everyone knows that the name of this family is to remember which family I belong to
大家知道這個家之就是念我是哪一個家族的
what is our family history
我們家族的歷史是什麼
You can read each other
你念對方就可以
You'll know how close you are to me
你會知道你跟我關係是多近多遠
Nearly pay 100 yuan
近一點就掏100塊
20 yuan for a little farther
遠一點給20塊
probably like this
大概就是這樣子
Said it took more than half a year
說花了半年多
Lost all others
把別人的全部賠了
this is for me
這個對我來講
that is to say I heard him say
就是說我聽到他這樣講
on the one hand very touched
一方面很感動
On the one hand it is a very special experience
一方面是一個很特別的經驗
why?
為什麼呢?
in Tibetan area
在藏腔族地區
there will never be such a thing
絕對不會有這樣子的事情
Because it's common for houses to burn down here
因為在這裡的屋子燒掉是很平常的事情
But except for the native people in the Tibetan area
但是除了本在之人在藏腔族地區
listen to you build the house
聽你把房子蓋起來
How can you possibly seek help from outsiders?
你怎麼可能從外面去找別人幫忙呢?
This is where the survivors are very powerful in the local area.
這個就是遺族在當地非常厲害的地方
Also from another point of view
另外從一個角度講
In the past, it was also a place where the survivors were considered very barbaric.
在以前也是遺族被認為是非常野蠻的地方
Why?
為什麼?
The bereaved are different from the Tibetan
遺族他們跟藏腔族不一樣
They dare to go out to open up wasteland and conquer the world
他們很敢出去開荒打天下
By what?
靠的是什麼?
historical memory
歷史記憶
plus historical memory
就是加之歷史記憶
So some Tibetans next to me know
所以旁邊的一些藏族都曉得
if you watch some survivors
如果你看了一些遺族
Two or three households have invaded your territory
兩三戶侵入到你的地盤
no one lives next to your mountain
在你的山旁邊沒有人住的地方
One day it suddenly started to smoke
有一天突然開始冒煙了
A few bereaved families came over there
那邊來了幾戶遺族
then you don't mess with him
然後你就不要去惹他
Because although there are two or three families
因為雖然是兩三戶人
He randomly finds hundreds of people to help fight
他隨便去找個幾百人來幫忙打架
Easy
很容易的
Why?
為什麼?
It is by this combined with diachronic memory
就是靠著這種加之歷時記憶
so here
所以在這邊
In the entire Sichuan border area
在整個四川這個川邊地區
pineapple seed dill
菠蘿子 蘿蘿
are all in
都是在
already in Sichuan dialect
已經在四川話裡面就是
scold strong and unreasonable people
罵強悍不講理的人
What does it mean?
其實指的是什麼?
This is what it meant
原來指的都是這個
The people from this side of Liangshan
這個這個梁山這邊的人
so i just said
所以我剛才有說
My friend from the field is in Ezi Village, Xiaoxin Country
我的田野的那個朋友在小信國埃齊村的
They are also called pineapple seeds
他們也被人家罵菠蘿子
Actually they are not pineapple seeds
其實他們不是菠蘿子
they are
他們是就是
Because of being barbaric, I was scolded for stripping naked
因為野蠻所以被人家罵剝裸子
Then other people's impression of them is
然後別人對他們的印象就是
Very able to mobilize people who increase capital to help fight
很能夠動員加資的人幫忙打架
They are feared by all ethnic groups in this place
他們在這個地方是所有的族群都怕他們
then what about them
然後他們呢
Each capital increase has its own family allowance
每個加資都有自己的家補
That is the name of men from generation to generation
那既在加資一代一代男子的名字
joint father and son
父子聯名
For example, he said that you see and hold the cloth
他譬如說你看取握取佈
Take the cloth, take the insert, take the ink
取佈取插取插墨兒
He even developed a way of changing memory
他就甚至於他發展一種變於記憶的方式
so many important wars
那麼很多的重要的戰爭
Both Qianxi and ancestors are recorded in this kind of history
謙喜跟祖先都記載在這種歷史裡面
This is me from a visit to a person
這個是我從一個訪問一個人
He wrote a book called "I Am Between Ghosts and Gods"
他寫了一本書叫《我在鬼神之間》
i visit his son
我訪問他兒子
his son wrote it with him
他兒子跟他一起寫的
He tells the history of their immediate family
他這個裡面講他們那個即刻家族的歷史
There are stories of brothers in this history
這種歷史裡面也有兄弟故事
But it's different from the gun bamboo
但是跟槍竹那邊的不一樣
He all started with hero ancestors
他都是從英雄祖先開始
It all started with some heroic ancestors
都是從一些英雄祖先開始
This is the score of the repertoire
這是曲目世卒的戲譜
you see the same
你看也是一樣
Both father and son
都是父子聯名
This is a big death
這是一個大的世卒
So why do you want to remember the history of the family?
所以大家看為什麼要記家之歷史呢?
Because of the families in black they often have wars
因為黑衣各家之他們經常有戰爭
I'm talking about the human ecology here
我講這邊這個人類生態
It has something to do with the large population here
跟這邊的人口多這有關係
Many of them are wars between yin relatives
很多是陰親家之之間的戰爭
Extraordinary
特別平凡
Those who were defeated moved away
戰敗的就因此遷走
So you remember the history of these old and new feuds
所以你記得這些新仇舊恨的歷史
Can help people in the family to leave the same enemy
可以幫助家之的人離開同仇
Then for the survivors who love to sign
然後對於愛頒籤的遺族人來講
Living through the history of the home
藉著家之歷史的住
can be found far away
可在遠地找到能投靠
That is, members of the family who help fight and borrow money
即幫忙打架借錢的家之成員
Listen to what they say about women in general
聽他們講說一般的女性
It is not necessary to be home
是不太需要被家之
usually male
通常是男性
But I also see some women who memorize their backs very well
但是我也看到有些女性家之背得很好的
It was the young man just now
也是剛才那個年輕人
Once I went to a village with him
有一次我跟他到一個村寨去
He ended up being crippled by a drunk old lady
結果他就被一個喝醉酒的老太太殘住
been talking for more than half an hour
一直講了半個多小時
Then the old lady let him go
後來老太太才放了他
I just watched him pay the old lady five dollars
我就看他掏了五塊錢給那個老太太
I said what's going on
我說 怎麼回事
He said, oops, that old lady carried her home away from me.
他說 哎呀 那個老太太太跟我背家之
I recited the last time when she was my aunt
背了最後 他是我姑奶奶的時候
I pay five dollars
我掏五塊錢
asked me to give him five bucks for a drink
要我給他五塊錢喝酒
So it's useful to look at the history
所以你看歷史是很有用的
this
這個
so let's take a look
所以我們來看一看
These histories of the three ethnic groups we just looked at
我們剛才看到的三個族群的這些歷史
and finally
還有最後呢
I noticed that for nearly a hundred years
我注意近百年來
At least that is if we don't know the earlier history
至少就是說我們如果不知道更早的歷史
very clear
很清楚
The distribution area of the survivors has been expanding
遺族的分布地它一直在擴張
It has something to do with it and the machine
就是跟它這個加之機器有關係
So this guy who lets us read history
所以這個可以讓我們讀歷史的人
to think about a problem
去思考一個問題
That is to say, are we humans the earliest
就是說我們人類是不是最早
live in a society like the stick gun
是住在像杖槍這樣子的社會
And history begins
而歷史讓人開始
Create more complex and larger societies
建立更複雜更大型的社會
start to expand
開始往外擴張
So we look inside the history
所以我們看歷史裡面
In fact, there are real and fictional stories
其實有真實有虛構的故事
the most important is
最重要的是
Let's look at it and see what kinds of their local history
我們看它看來那幾種他們當地的歷史
in this historical narrative
這個歷史敘事裡面
often follow a certain structure
常常依循了某一種結構
Like the structure of the brothers we talked about
像我們講的那個弟兄的結構
What kind of structure is there like a big bird?
還有什麼大鴻鳥的那種結構
we can ask
我們可以這樣問
Is it because the stick guns and their culture were relatively backward in the past?
是不是過去杖槍他們文化比較落後
So they remember and uncle's
所以他們記得和叔叔的
history is not true
歷史不真實
and looking for some narrative structure
並尋著一些敘事結構
Then don't we?
那我們就沒有嗎?
not actually
其實並不是
I later wrote a book
我後來寫了一本書
It's called "Heroic Ancestors and Brotherly Nation"
叫《英雄祖先與弟兄民族》
is to analyze all those in Chinese history
就是分析所有中國歷史上的那些
History from the Emperor
從皇帝的歷史開始
actually i found
其實我發現
history as we know it
我們所熟悉的歷史
Also looking for a narrative mode
也尋著一個敘事模式
History relative to sibling ancestors
相對於弟兄祖先的歷史
what we know
我們所熟知的
is a heroic ancestral history
是一種英雄祖先歷史
These are two different histories
這是兩種不一樣的歷史
new product
新興的產物
Emerging history I mean a social culture
歷史新興我是指一種社會文化
it makes us unknowingly
它讓我們不知不覺的
just looking for a certain pattern
就尋著某一種模式
to remember and write history
來記憶跟書寫歷史
So look at this example I gave
所以你看我舉的這個例子
This is very famous in Chinese history
這是在中國歷史上很有名的
many historians
很多歷史學家
I always thought it was the real word
一直認為這是真詞發聲的
A Heroic Ancestor in the Northeast
東北一個英雄祖先
Ji Zi, Prince of Yin, Runs to North Korea
殷的王子 基子奔于朝鲜
Be a hero to civilize the Korean people
成为开化朝鲜人的英雄
prince of a southeastern state
东南一个州的王子
run from here to here
从这里跑到这里
enlightened
他就被成为开化
The heroic ancestors of the present Nanjing and Shanghai generations
现在南京上海一代的人的英雄祖先
A general of the state of Chu ran from here to here
一个楚国的将军从这里跑到这里
becomes a conquest
就变成征服
Kingdom
殿国的
become king here
在这里变成殿王
To the northwest, Tao Nutao of Qin State came here
往西北一个秦国的陶奴陶到这里
The locals regard Tao as the king
本地人就奉陶为王
think about it
大家想想看
this history
这个历史
Is there any structure
有没有结构
is there a pattern
有没有模式
The first one has the pattern
第一个它有个模式
all a hero
都是一个英雄
and all failed
而且都是失败的
frustrated hero
受挫折的英雄
right
对不对
Then if we know later
然后我们如果知道了以后
actually you see
其实你看
It is actually the symbol of these heroes
它其实这些英雄的符号
It corresponds to the Central Plains Huaxia at that time
它就对应了当时的中原华夏
these are the histories
就是这些历史
both appear in probably
都出现在大概是
Between the 1st and 5th centuries AD
公元一世纪到五世纪之间
In Shiji Hanshu and later Hanshu these
在史记汉书后汉书这些
in these records
這些記載裡面
So it actually represents
所以其實代表的是
Zhongyuan Huaxia's thoughts on the Quartet crowd
中原華夏對四方人群的想法
Simply speaking
簡單的講
Zhongyuan Huaxia hopes that people on both sides
中原華夏希望這兩邊的人
is part of Huaxia
是華夏的一部分
So give them two more distinguished ancestors
所以給他們兩個比較尊貴的祖先
see if you want to accept
看你要不要接受
southwest a little hesitant
西南有點猶豫
Give him a general of Chu
給他一個楚國的將軍
to this northwest
對這個西北的
That's Tao Nu
那是陶奴
that's even worse
那個就更差了
so you see
所以你看
then this
那麼這個
Do you mean history?
你說是不是歷史呢?
Do you care about this history?
大家關不關心這個歷史呢?
Koreans now care about the history of the machine very much
現在的韓國人非常在乎機子的歷史
so it's still fighting
所以現在還在爭
since the twelfth century
十二世紀以來
People on the Korean peninsula are very concerned about the history of the machine
朝鮮半島人就非常在乎機子的歷史
since modern times
那近代以來
They have two discourses
他們有兩種論述
First
第一個
machine is myth
機子就是神話
wrong
不對的
That's fine, just ignore him
那個可以就不要理他就好了
The second argument is that
第二個論述就是說
The machine is actually our Korean
機子其實就是我們韓國人
In fact, the original territory
其實原來的領土
In the current Chinese train
就在現在的中國機列
So Jilin Province belongs to our Korea
所以吉林省是我們韓國的
This must be controversial, right?
這個就一定會有爭議了對不對
how to explain history
如果這樣子解釋歷史
There is no dispute about Southeast
還有東南這個沒有爭議
Everyone believes that people in Jiangnan really believe in the history of Taibo Benwu
大家都相信江南的人很相信太伯奔武的歷史
So you can still see the Taibo Temple when you go there
所以你到那邊去還可以看到太伯廟
There are Taibo Temples in many places
很多地方都有太伯廟
Southwest from Four Seasons
西南從十四季以後
The four seasons of Zhuangqiao are written in all the square characters of Yunnan
莊橋的這個四季就寫入所有雲南的方字裡面
Northwest they don't care
西北他們根本不在乎
I don't care what you say I am
你說我是什麼我根本不在乎
He doesn't care about this history of ignorance and foresight
他不在乎這個無與遠見的歷史
So everyone pay attention to what I want to say
所以我要講的大家注意
The content of history may have truth
歷史的內容可能有真實
But the main fiction lies in the relationship between history and the human rights in power
但是主要的虛構在於歷史跟當權人權的關係
In other words, why do Koreans care about the machine?
也就是說韓國人為什麼要在乎機子
He thinks it seems that the machine has something to do with the current people in Korea
他認為好像機子跟韓國的現在的人有關係
In fact, no matter whether this history is true or not
其實不管這個歷史是真實不真實
The biggest fiction lies in these characters in history
最大的虛構是在於歷史裡面的這些人物
Whether it's a brother or a hero
不管是弟兄或者是英雄
relationship with present
跟現在人的關係
that is a very big fiction
那個是一個非常大的虛構
Let's see
大家來看
Creation and belief in the history of our brethren's ancestors
創作及相信弟兄祖先歷史的
The existence of this kind of gun bamboo
這種槍竹的存在人群
Everyone I didn't talk about here
大家我剛才沒有講在這裡
you can notice
大家可以注意到
What is so special about this history?
這個歷史有什麼特別呢?
this history because it is a past
這個歷史因為它就是一個過去
then combine with now
然後跟現在結合在一起
So in this history
所以這種歷史裡面
The reality created by that history is
那種歷史造成的現實是
There is no distinction between conquerors and conquered
沒有征服者和被征服者的區分
There is no distinction between old residents and new residents
也沒有老居民跟新居民的區分
But the history of such heroic ancestors as we believe
但是我們所相信的這種英雄祖先的歷史
I can say
我可以說
The so-called we are the whole world
所謂的我們是全世界
people of the so-called civilized world
所謂的文明世界的人
This is the hero we believe in
我們相信的都是這種英雄
Whether it's the emperor, Tan Jun, Chen Jinsihan, Abraham
不管是皇帝 談軍 陳金斯漢 亞波拉漢
What about the history of the holding group?
持组的历史呢
or Immigrant Heroes to the present May issue
或者是到现在5月号号的移民英雄
and the American history of the heroes who founded the country and unblocked the black slaves
和开国立项解封黑奴的英雄的美国史
and emphasizing the history of Taiwan's history of the heroic attacks on the Policy Workers Awards
和强调政策工奖中正等英雄攻击的台湾史
They are all the products of a kind of heroic history.
都是一种英雄主习的历史新兴下的产物
arises out of the above internal group distinction
就产生于以上这个内部族群区分
there are conquerors
有征服者
you just have to believe the history
你只要相信这些历史
Now there is a distinction between the conqueror and the conquered
现在就有征服者和被征服的区分
There is a distinction between old residents and new immigrants
有老居民跟新移民的区分
So actually do you think
所以还是其实你觉得
What is the difference between those of us and those of the powerful or the Tibetans?
我们这些跟强主的那些或藏族的差别在哪里
same structure
一样的有结构
And what?
而且呢
Where is the same biggest fiction?
同样的最大的虚构是在哪里呢
It's the relationship between the hero and the crowd
是在这英雄跟现在人群的关系
like in the US
比如说在美国
often the mayflower immigrant
常常5月花号移民
It seems to be related to all the days
好像跟所有的白日都有关系
How could it be
其实怎么会
right
对不对
In Taiwan, it seems that all the people from other provinces will tell you
在台湾好像所有的外省人都会跟你讲
Anti-China is related
反中正有關係
All Hokkien people will be related to Zheng Chenggong
所有的閩南人都會跟鄭成功有關係
Actually not
其實都不會
right
對不對
Those are all some imaginations generated through this kind of history
那個都是一個透過這種歷史產生的一些想像
So even if the heroic epic is true
所以即使英雄史詩是真的
whatever those machines
不管是那些機子什麼
even if it's true
即使是真的
He and the current group
他和當前的族群
For example, the relationship between the emperor and the Han people
譬如說皇帝跟漢人的關係
are imagined and constructed
都是想像和建構的
so
所以
Finally I'm going to use this to illustrate my entire point above
最後我要用這個來說明我前面的整個的point
It's like the movie Matrix
這就是像電影駭客任務
the metrics
那個metrics
inside the plot
裡面的情節
that plot is
那個情節是
At that time, most people lived in the virtual world created by the computer city
當時大多數的人都活在由電腦城市創造的虛擬世界裡面
In fact, we are living in the real world constructed by history.
其實我們是活在歷史建構的現實世界
And we get a certain identity in this world
而且我們在這個世界裡面得到特定的身份認同
we're sending a memory
我們要發出一個記憶
So because we believe in history
所以因為我們因為相信歷史
Accepting one's social status on the fringes
接受自身邊緣的社會地位
Like a person stepping on a sharp stone with bare feet
如同人赤腳踩在一個尖銳的石頭上
don't know pain
不知道痛
There is no movement of pulling the foot back
沒有抽回腳的這個動作
Or because we believe in and care about history
或者我們因為相信並在乎歷史
we have something as
我們有一些作為
result of what we did
結果我們的所作所為
create an appearance
造成一種表象
And let the world created by history
而讓歷史所創造的世界
become more real
變得更真實
so then
所以那麼
How can we know the reality of the real world
我們如何可能認識這個現實世界的本象
How do you realize the meaning of your actions?
如何體認自身作為的意義呢
I've been advocating a kind of reflective historiography research lately
我最近是在提倡一種反思史學的研究
But mostly these are used in
但最主要這些是用在
research on ethnic minorities in China
對中國少數民族的研究上
Actually my example just now
其實我剛才的例子
the one i lifted
我舉的那個
also some ethnic minorities
也是一些少數民族
Let's say you accept a history
譬如說你接受了一個歷史
This history makes you a minority
這個歷史讓你成為少數民族
Do you think I'm a minority?
你認為我是少數民族嗎?
right?
對不對?
All your deeds have proved
你的所有的作為反而去印證了
Your marginalization of this minority in the mainstream society
你的讓這種少數民族在整個主流社會裡面的邊緣地位
more and more solid, more and more real
越來越穩固、越來越真實
you'll always be on the edge
你就永遠居於那種邊緣的地位
So the reflective historiography I advocate
所以我提倡的這種反思史學
It is hoped that through some concepts and research methods
是希望透過一些概念和研究方法
Let's not just be historians
讓我們其實不只是歷史學者
I also hope that individuals in general will be able to reflect on our pre-existing historical knowledge
我也希望一般個人能夠反思我們既有的歷史知識
to unearth some of the cognitive biases lurking in our minds
來發掘潛藏在我們心中的一些認知偏見
To understand the various social and cultural structures that influence our perception and construction of history
來認識影響我們認知和建構歷史的種種社會文化結構
In this way, our understanding of the reality of society and its historical changes
藉此我們對於社會的現實本項和它的歷史變遷
may have further understanding
可能有進一步的了解
Thus there may be some reflective action
因而可能有一些反思性的行動
I want to create reflective knowledge
我是希望創造有反思性的知識
reflective cognition
反思性認知
and individuals capable of reflective action
和有反思性行動能力的個人
Even if these actions are very small
這些行動即使是非常的微小
can also gradually change the society
也可以逐漸的改變這個社會
thank you guys i will stop here today
謝謝各位 我今天就講到這裡
it doesn't matter
沒有關係 可以
Thank you teacher for your wonderful speech
謝謝老師精彩的演講
i want to ask
我想請教就是說
Suppose we learn according to reflection
假設我們依照反思使學
Try to think about yourself or your society
去努力的想自己或是想自己的社會
How do I know if we all or myself
我要怎麼知道說我們大家或是我自己
will get closer to the truth
會越來越接近本相
Or do I jump from one surface appearance to another
還是說我從一個表面表象跳到另一個表象
I use an example from my book
我用我的書裡面用的一個例子
A research method I suggest
我建議的一種研究方法
In fact, this research method is also related to my multi-point fields.
其實這種研究方法跟我的多點田也有關係
That is, if we take that history as a representation
就是說如果我們把那個歷史當作一個表象的話
That means I'm at Icgo's place
就是說我在Icgo那個地方
I observe their social reality
我觀察他們的社會本象
I believe I'm not seeing the real image
我相信我沒有看到真實的本象
That said I have a lot of my biases
就是說我有很多我的偏見
then I record their history
那麼我記錄他們的歷史
that's a sign
那是一個表象
what is this like
這就像什麼呢
I watch it with an Out of the Mirror
我用一個Out of the Mirror來看
if i put my watch on the table
如果我把我的表放在桌上
If I look at this watch with an Out of the Mirror
我用一個Out of the Mirror來看這個表的話
Then all I saw was some of this Out of the Mirror
那我看到的只是這個Out of the Mirror上的一些
distorted some shapes
被扭曲的一些形狀
Then how can I get a better understanding
那我怎麼樣可以比較進一步的認識
The way I suggest is to move this Out of the Mirror
我建議的方法就是移動這個Out of the Mirror
you move the angle of observation
你移動觀察的角度
or move it to see another object
或移動它來看另外一個物體
Then watch the change of its appearance
然後看它這個表象的變化
Actually this is my field
其實這個就是我的田野
I look everywhere
我在每一個地方去觀察
The image of society in every place
這個每一個地方的社會的本象
But I'm not sure if my observation is right or wrong
但是我不確定我觀察的對或錯
But I record these their histories
但是我記錄這些他們的歷史
or some myths and legends
或一些神話傳說
I take these as appearances
這些我把它當作表象
Then I went to compare the changes in this appearance
然後我去比較這個表象的變化
Then this time actually this
然後這個時候其實這個
I can't stress enough that
我非常強調的一點是
This approach does not allow us
這種方法並沒有讓我們
Absolutely understand the underlying phenomenon
絕對的去認識底下的這個本象
But it can teach us about our biases
但是它可以讓我們認識我們的偏見
That is the nature of this concave-convex mirror
也就是這個凹凸鏡的性子
Is this a concave mirror or a convex mirror?
這是一個凹鏡還是一個凸鏡
I think this explanation should be ok
我想這個解釋應該可以吧
Thanks
謝謝
He said it was devil's beer
他说这是鬼子的啤酒
don't drink
不喝
then i'll be fine
那我就好
I went to buy Taiwan beer for him to drink
我再去买了台湾啤酒给他喝
Then just talk and start talking
然后就讲就开始就话题
They came from Harbin in the northeast
他们从东北哈尔滨过来
about the third century
大概三世纪上
also said education
还都说过教育
They still call the Japanese devils
他们到现在还称日本人是鬼子
Here is an example
这是一个例子
The second example is my brother in Shanghai
第二个例子是我弟弟在上海
he has a daughter
他有个女儿
I am ten years old and studying in Shanghai
今年十岁在上海念书
He needs a red scarf when he goes to school
他上学的时候要啤一个红领巾
he told him honestly
他老实告诉他
This red scarf was
这个红领巾是当年
When the Japanese killed us Chinese
当年日本人杀我们中国人的时候
Write the bonus of feelings first
先写感情的红利金
we want to remember forever
我们要一辈子记得
This life impresses me deeply
这一生让我很印象很深刻
The relationship between China and Japan is so deep
中国跟日本关系这么深厚
They used hatred from childhood
他们从小就用仇恨的方式
come to teach how to treat the Japanese
来教育要对待日本人
How will the two succeed after renting
这两名租以后怎么相继
how come
怎么得了
He used hatred at such a young age
他这么小就用仇恨的方式
What should I do if I recognize this renter?
认断这名租怎么办
No, I saw the National Taiwan University History Hell Professor
不是我又看到台大史地狱教授
he has an article saying
他有篇文章说
Just don't teach history
干脆历史别教
Because it's all ideology
因为都是意识形态
After teaching for a long time, I was right
教了半天都是我有理
It's because others don't understand
都是别人没理
we want to hate
我们要仇恨
this worries me very much
这个让我非常忧心
Should we study history in the next generation?
我们在下一代到底要不要读历史
Why do we care
Why do we care
what did we learn about history
我们到底学了历史
What we learned about CSI
我们以前学的讲中证什么
It turned out that many of them were not
后来发现很多不是这样的
not all like this
不都是这样的
I took a lot of big classes
我上了很多的大课
so i feel distressed
所以我觉得很苦惱
many hours of driving
搭了很多小时的车
come ask the teacher to listen
来请老师听教
Thanks
谢谢
I think that's the great challenge we historians face
我想這是我們歷史學家所面對的很大的挑戰
This indeed means that between each country
這個的確現在就是說每一個國家之間
will emphasize some of these histories
都是會強調一些這些歷史
But at the same time we will forget some history
但是同時我們也會遺忘一些歷史
So sometimes I will suddenly ask some mainland Chinese scholars
所以我有的時候會突然問一些中國大陸學者
Some questions are like provocation
一些問題像是挑撥理件
I said that a Jiangsu native once killed 800,000 of your Hebei native
我說有個江蘇人曾經殺過你們那個河北人的80萬
what no one knows
什麼沒有人知道
I said that person's name is Xiang Yu
我說那個人叫向雨
Xiang Yu once killed that, this, 800,000
向雨曾經坑殺那個這個80萬
that's all
就這些就是說
Because people think we're one country now
因為大家認為我們現在是一個國家
right it's not important
對不對這就不是重要的事情
In fact, our history has been a little forgotten
其實我們的歷史一直在一些遺忘
Then I'm thinking about the real history education
那我在想真的這個歷史教育
I think my ideal is
我覺得我的理想是
Of course we are still in a certain country
當然我們還是在某一種國家
We are in Taiwan, or you are in China, right?
我們在台灣,或者你是中國,對不對?
or every country, so your history
或者每一個國家,所以你的歷史
Still can't go too far beyond the interests of this country
還是不能夠太超越這個國家的利益啊
or something
或者什麼這些
But I feel our little child
但是我是覺得到了我們的小孩子
in senior year
到了高年級的時候
For example, in the third year of high school
比如說到了高三
or in college
或者在大學裡的時候
we will have this
我們會有這種
Combining historical memory with some aspects of social science
把歷史記憶跟社會科學的一些
Basic courses in this category
這一類的基本的課程
let him know
讓他知道
The relationship between his identity and history
他的認同跟歷史之間的關係
In this way, I feel that such a person
這樣子我是覺得這樣一個人
his future
他對自己的未來
There will be some reflective choices
會有一些反思性的抉擇
rather than exactly this
而不是完全這種
history of nationalism
國主主義的歷史
caused by the kind
所造成的那種
This conflict between nations and nations
國家國家民族跟民族之間的這種衝突
Of course we will also do some
當然我們也會做一些
Like me and Professor Huang Zhijing here
像我跟在座這個黃志敬教授
we also have cooperation
我們也有合作
Do something like this in Northeast Asia
做一些譬如說東北亞的這些
For example, history
譬如說歷史
Let's see if we can come up with a historical explanation
看看我們能不能提出一種歷史解釋
Let Korea Japan China Taiwan
讓韓國 日本 中國 台灣
Acceptable by several of our countries
我們幾個國家都能夠接受的
some northeast asian history
一些東北亞歷史
Especially about the so-called Manchuria
特別是關於所謂的滿洲
Or the history of this place in the Northeast
或者是東北這個地方的歷史
because of the history here
因為這邊的歷史
It is related to the plot between several countries
關係到幾個國家之間的情節
historical plot
歷史情節
ask the professor
請教教授
very old history
很古老的歷史
But because of the different generations
但是因為世代的不同
Views and hatred of history
對歷史的看法跟仇恨
or what seems to keep evolving different views
或什麼好像會一直演變不同的看法
Is it the same with the angle?
跟角度是不是會這樣
Yes, of course that means
對 那當然就是說
History and our personal
歷史跟我們個人的
Actually what I just said
其實我剛剛講的
with our personal identification
跟我們個人的認同
with where we are
跟我們所處的
Reality matters
現實的狀況有關係
And often when we write history
而且常常我們在寫歷史的時候
we are influenced by some structures
我們受到一些結構的影響
For example, I just mentioned a structure called historical emerging
譬如說我剛才只提到一種結構叫歷史新興
In fact, there are many
其實還有很多
let me give you an example
譬如說我舉一個例子
Chinese Fangzi Tradition
中國的方字傳統
right
對不對
When Taiwan was included in the territory of the Qing Empire
當台灣被進入了大清帝國的版圖了以後
Usually magistrates come here
通常地方官到了這邊來
in any frontier area
在任何邊疆的地區
The first and foremost thing is called
第一個首要的事情叫
Gather local intellectuals to write square characters
召集地方知識分子寫方字
when you write square characters
當你在寫方字的時候
Note that square characters are a genre
大家注意方字是一種文類
Genre means that it has a certain structure
文類的意思是它有一定的結構
certain way of writing
一定的寫法
The genre of square characters naturally allows you to write a
方字的文類自然而然讓你寫出一個
Suitable square characters
適合的方字
And then turned Taiwan into a part of the whole big empire
然後把台灣變成了整個大帝國的一部分
This doesn't just happen in Taiwan
這個不只是發生在台灣
Any Yunnan is the same
任何雲南什麼都一樣
the way I've been looking for
一直要尋的方式
It is a very interesting example that I studied before
就是我以前研究一個很有趣的一個例子
the structure of history
這種歷史的結構
There is a guy from Yunnan who is very interesting
有一個雲南人他特別有意思
He has been very this and this all his life
他一生中都非常的這個這個
When it's time to indulge
該縱舉的時候縱舉
When it's time to be an official
該當官的時候當官
Then teach when it's time to retire
然後該退休講學的時候就講學
As a result, in later years
結果後來到晚年的時候
He is in charge of compiling a way of Yunnan
他去負責編一個雲南的方式
As a result, he wrote a method
結果他寫出了一個方式呢
It's not suitable for square characters
居然是不合方字文類
The result, the result, everyone knows what the result will be
結果結果大家知道結果會怎麼樣
Everyone knows this word
大家知道這個編方字
There is another organizational structure called Fang Zi Bureau
還有一個組織結構叫做方字局
it's not his business
不是他一個人的事情
it's a group of people thing
是一群人的事情
As a result, his way was caught by his colleagues
結果他的方式就被他的同事呢
this is not acceptable
這個不能接受
He left angrily
他就憤而稀搞離去
so everyone knows
所以大家知道
Not just square characters
不只是方字文類
will guarantee you a history like square characters
會保證你一個方字那樣子的歷史
right
對不對
so everyone can
所以大家就能夠
To find a certain rule and write it out
要尋著一定的規律寫出來
This kind of organizational genre can also guarantee a square character
這樣子的組織文類也可以要保證一個方字
right
對不對
Then the text of this square character comes out
然後這個方字的文本出來
proves that place is part of the whole
就證明地方是整體的一部分
that's what tells us
這就是告訴我們
we write a lot
我們很多的書寫
are influenced by some of our writing structures
都受到我們的一些書寫結構
Our culture
我們的文化
The impact of our various social organizations
我們的各種的社會組織的影響
In fact, there is another one that I haven't explained very clearly here.
更其實還有一個我這邊沒有講得很清楚
is the symbol
就是符號
Symbolic meaning
符號意義
In fact, it was mentioned just now
其實剛才其實也提到了
like those brethren symbols
像那些弟兄符號
pair hero symbol
對 英雄符號
symbol of a hero
作為英雄符號的
Like those machines, taber
譬如說那些機子 泰伯
And the Jiang Zongzheng we talked about in Taiwan
和我們在台灣講的這個蔣宗正
Zheng Chenggong
鄭成功
inside each symbol
每一個符號裡面
They all have some inner connotations in the eyes
都帶有了一些內在的一些眼神的意涵
not who it appears to be
不是它表面所指的那個人
and more meaning
而且更多的意涵
affect our identification
會影響到我們的認同
right
對
i will give him to you
我會把他給你
I ask you how much
我問你幾萬一下
I think our Chinese history
我覺得我們的中國歷史上
because some things are
因為有些事情就是
every emperor dies
每個皇帝死掉
Only one head can change his name
只要一頭頭才可以給他改的一個名字
you are sure
你才確定下來
If the emperor had not died
假如說皇帝還沒有死之前
he doesn't know his life
他不知道他的生命
his future behavior is influenced by
他對將來的行為是受到的影響
Because you think don't get a quick review
因為你覺得不要得到一個很快的評價
History should be leveled
歷史要平整
This concept seems to be unique to China.
這種觀念好像是中國才有的
don't understand this
不懂這個事
In addition to that
另外就是說
same basis
同樣的根據
form of confirmation
證實的形作
like until the qing dynasty
像一直到清朝
The history of the Ming Dynasty was written by the Qing Dynasty
寫了明朝歷史是有清朝的寫
The Republic of China should write history
中華民國應該寫要寫歷史
For example, the history of the Republic of China
比如說中華民國歷史
Who is he to write
是他誰來寫
these are some questions
這都是一些問題
In fact, I feel like Guoshu people, the original staff should do this
事實上,我覺得像國術人,本來的工作人員應該要做這件事情
He's not doing it now, probably can't do it, can't do it
他現在沒有在做,可能也做不到,做不成
This is what seems to have been done historically
這是好像歷史上應該去做的事情
is it possible to invite them to come
是不是可以請他們來
I may only be able to answer part of your question, the question about verification
我可能只能回答你部分的問題,就是關於證實的問題
Confirmation is also a genre like the one I just mentioned
證實也是像我剛才所講的一種文類
It also has a certain format
它也是有一定的格式的
And this is very interesting, in my research on reflective history
而且這個是非常有意思的,在我的反思史學的研究
That is to say, my interpretation of some historical texts
就是說我對於一些歷史文本的解讀
It may be different from the general and traditional interpretation methods
跟一般的可能有些傳統的解讀方法不一樣
I'll treat it as one, it'll correspond to a situation
我會把它當作是一個,它會跟一個情境對應的
That is, there is a corresponding relationship between text and context
就是text跟context它有個對應的關係
Just under a certain context, you will generate such text
就在某種context之下,你會產生那樣的text
that historical text
那種歷史文本
If that kind of structural context is like the Central Plains Empire
那一種結構性的一種 context 如果像中原帝國
it produces a structured text
它就會產生一種結構性的文本
That's the proof we're talking about you just mentioned
那就是我們講的你剛才提到的證實
So you see that the emergence of the confirmation is in the Qin Han Empire
所以你看證實的出現是在禽漢帝國
Right, when China's first unified empire emerged
對不對 中國最早的統一帝國出現的時候
it appeared
它出現了
Then when it comes to Qing History, it can barely become the last proof
然後到了清史是勉強可以成為最後一部證實
You can see that text and context are consistent
你看這個是 text 跟 context 是相始終的
right
對不對
When the context of the entire Central Plains Empire appeared, it was confirmed to appear
那個整個中原帝國的 context 出現的時候證實出現
The Central Plains Empire is over
中原帝國結束了
it just ends
它就跟著結束
So it has a corresponding relationship
所以它是有個對應關係的
So from this point of view
所以從這一點來講
If we're going to write Taiwan's history or something now
如果我們現在要寫台灣的歷史或什麼
Of course, it is impossible for us to find the format of proof to write
當然我們不可能去尋著證實的這種格式來寫
even in mainland China
即使在中國大陸
I'm thinking there's one that everyone can be very suspicious of paying attention to.
我在想有一個大家可以很疑於去注意的
This is a large-scale compilation in mainland China
這是中國大陸在大規模的編寫
Bi-Historical Project
親史工程
So what kind of family history will be compiled in the end?
所以最後會編出來什麼樣一個親史
This pro-history and the original official history structure
這個親史跟原來的正史結構
what difference does it make
它到底有什麼樣的差別
I think that tells us a lot
我覺得那個透露給我們非常多的訊息
Excuse me
請問
give that first
先給那個
I am like this
我是這樣
I read a little history myself because I'm an amateur
我自己因為我就是業餘讀一點歷史
that is sometimes a little worrying
那個有時候會有一點憂心
Are we advocating a historical attitude
是不是我們提倡一種歷史的態度
when we study history
就是就是我們讀歷史的時候
be humble
可以謙虛一點
That is to say, our Chinese nation is not that great
就是說其實我們中華民族沒有那麼偉大
Yes or no
是不是
Even the nations are really not so great
它就是各個民族也真的沒有這麼偉大
when we read history
我們在他們在念歷史的時候
When washing history, the so-called formal
洗历史的时候所谓正式过
It will shape our national self-confidence
它要塑造我们的民族自信心
let them
让他们
For example, from the perspective of various ethnic plots involving various aspects
比如说从籌涉各方面的各种民族情节也好
But because this situation is different from other countries
但是因为这种情形上跟别的国家是
There will be quotas and conflicts
是会有干额 会有冲突的时候
So shall we adopt a more modest historical attitude?
所以我们是不是提上一种比较谦虚的历史态度
can be compared
可以比较
like in this sense
像就这个意义上来看
It is very meaningful for you to study the history of ethnic minorities
您研究少数民族的历史是非常有意义的
because it can be compared to some
因为可以比出一些
Chauvinism of the Han Nationality Chauvinism of the Great Qing Dynasty
汉族的沙文主义 大清武的沙文主义
Looking at the history of this minority
在这少数民族的历史上来看比较
Like you take this Otto
像您把这个奥托境一下
can have a clearer career
可以有更更比较清楚的事业
Is this attitude true?
是不是这个态度是挺到实际上
OK
OK
Thanks
谢谢
My ideas may be more radical than yours
我的想法可能比你想得更激进
I just think we have to reflect on those
我是根本就是觉得我们要去反思那些
Whether it is the Chinese nation or all nations
不管是中华民族 或所有的民族
or the concept of ethnic minorities
或少数民族这种概念
I was in a speech not long ago
我前不久才在一个演讲里面
tell my audience
跟我的听众说
We even develop a sense of beauty
我們甚至會培養一種美感
on a hillside
一片山坡上
How many of these thatched cottages are there?
有幾棟這個毛草房
or a stone house
或者石頭器的房子
we think it is a kind of beauty
我們認為是一種美
Because this is called the little tree nation
因為這個是叫小樹民族
Or the settlement of the Round Treemen
或者叫圓樹民的聚落
And if there is a sun room
而這裡面如果有一棟陽房
We feel that the unbeautiful destroys the beauty
我們就覺得那個不美破壞了美
why do we have to
為什麼我們自己要
They all live in this very high-end sun room
都住在這個非常高檔的陽房裡面
we encourage some people
我們鼓勵一些人
to practice that beauty
去實踐那種美感
to live in thatched huts and stone huts
去住在毛草屋和石頭屋裡
Why do we call culture
為什麼我們所謂的文化
Our culture is placed in the Palace Museum
我們的文化是放在故宮博物院
or where is this
或者是在哪邊的這個
inside these museums
這些博物館裡面
And some people are called the little tree people
而有一些人叫做小樹民族
round tree people
叫做圓樹民
must be in daily life
必須要在日常生活裡面
to practice their culture
去實踐他們的文化
practice their traditional culture
實踐他們的傳統文化
Actually I think we have a lot of this
其實我覺得我們有很多的這種
such a misunderstanding
這種一種誤解
or this illusion
或者是這種錯覺
all because of our commitment to the entire
都是因為我們對整個
This society does not have a real understanding of some of our appearances
這個社會對我們的一些表象沒有一個真正的認知
My name is Lin and my name is Lin Nonghai
我姓林 我叫林農海
my teacher has a historical perspective
我老師有歷史的觀點
Now in this world, let's say IS
現在這個世界 比方說IS
They kill people indiscriminately
他們這個這個亂殺人
without this humanity
沒有這個人性
Then the United States should help them
那麼美國要幫助他們
He also attacked IS
結果他也是攻擊IS
But there are many refugees
但是這個難民很多
America is empathetic too
美國也是同理心
$4 billion and more recently $4 billion
40億美金還有最近又40億美金
to finish this
要完治這個這個
But the Soviet Union
可是這個蘇聯
He's going to this series
他要到這個這個系列
do you know
要不知道要
To help IS, or how to help, to unrest
要幫助IS,或是幫助怎麼樣,要動亂
so i want to remember this
所以這個我要想起來
I think of Huaguo National Limitable
就想到華國國民Limitable
that miserable world
那個悲慘世界
I've read a lot of the writings of this legacy country
這個遺國的書寫的,我讀了很多
this inside this
這個裡面的這個
Let's do some research and see what can be done
來研究,看看有什麼辦法
this to solve
這個來解決
I'm not trying to panic, and I'm not here to help over there.
不是要恐後,也不是要來幫助那邊
Help here, expand your own establishment
幫助這邊,就擴充自己的樹立
have empathy, have sympathy
要有同理心,要同情
To see how the world will change
要看看這個世界要怎麼樣改變
Thanks
謝謝
thanks i think this we all agree
謝謝,我想這個,我們大家都同意了
you are judging by history
你就是由歷史來看
I look at history
我由歷史來看
So for this IS question
所以對於這個IS的問題
this
這個
i didn't
我是沒有
I can't say his brother because I don't do research on that
我沒辦法說他哥因為我不做那方面的研究
but i can only say
但是我只能說
Do you feel a little hot
你覺得有點氣溫
good
好
I will briefly talk about some of my views
我大略的講一下我的一些看法
In fact, not long ago I
其實我在前不久
Because I was in Yinchuan not long ago
因為我前不久在銀川
I also gave a speech in a university for nationalities
還在一個民族大學裡面做一個演講
Many of my audience are muslims
我底下的觀眾很多都是穆斯林
The topic I'm talking about is related to my gun post research.
我講的這個題目是跟我的槍柱研究有關的
There's a Poison Cat Tale Over the Gun Post
槍柱那邊有個毒藥貓的故事
Lets say some women in a village are poison cats
就講一個村子裡面有一些女人是毒藥貓
In fact, I simply say
其實我簡單的講
This kind of legend is the same as the story of the witch in the West
這種傳說故事跟西方的女巫的故事是一樣的
the real behind it
它背後的真正的
This is if it is a text
這個是如果是一個text
This legend is treated as a text
這種傳說當作一個text
Behind the context
後面的context
It is the marginal status of women in a community.
就是女性在一個社區裡面的邊緣地位
And such a community is a place that emphasizes purity
而這樣子的社區又是一個很強調純正
A community that emphasizes boundaries
很強調邊界的社區
will produce this
就會產生這種
We're a phenomenal phenomenon in research
我們在研究上成為帶綽高揚現象
in this way
這樣子
In fact, there are many problems of this kind in this IS
其實這個IS的很多這一類的問題
In fact, it's all about the purity in it.
其實都是這種裡面的純淨主義
everyone is not just this
大家不只是這個
In fact, in many human groups
其實在人類很多的群體裡面
Everyone emphasizes boundaries, emphasizing purity
大家都強調邊界 強調純淨
In fact, this is a lot of human
其實這個是人類的很多的
These suspicions, some of the roots of violent conflict
這些猜疑 暴力衝突的一些根源
this subtitle of my speech
我那個演講的這個副標題
It is called the source of fear, suspicion and violence of human beings.
就叫人類的這個恐懼猜疑與暴力根源
but today there is no way to talk about this
不過今天沒有辦法談到這個
If you are interested, you can find me
如果大家有興趣的話可以找我的那個
In fact, you hit the poisonous cat on the Internet
其實你上網打毒藥貓三個字
After that there was a lot of discussion
之後就有很多的討論
In my book "Shooting Between Han and Tibetans"
在我的那本書《槍戰漢藏之間》
There's also a specialization on that poison cat phenomenon.
裡面也有專長討論那個毒藥貓現象
Thanks
謝謝
Yuan Shihao, I would like to ask how the difference in the history of the ancestors came about
袁世豪我想請問一下祖先歷史的差異是怎麼產生的
Then why now it seems that the history of most countries is built on the history of heroic ancestors
然後為什麼就現在好像多數的國家的歷史都是建構在英雄祖先歷史之上
Then it seems that most of the aborigines and primitive tribes we think of are based on the history of brothers
然後好像我們所認為的那些原住民跟原始部落好像多半是以弟兄歷史
It is brothers, ancestors, history is the main
就是弟兄祖先歷史為主
So is there any type of ancestry history other than these two? Thanks
那除了這兩類的祖先歷史之外還有什麼類型的祖先歷史嗎?謝謝
This question is very good, just now I didn't make it very clear, I can add now
這問題很好正好我剛才沒有講得很清楚我現在可以補充一下
So think about it, these two are different societies, one is a continuous society
所以想想看就是這兩種是不同的社會一個是一種接續的社會
That is, you have a ruling class and then there are layers of rulers underneath
就是你有統治階層然後底下有一層一層的統治者
Then there are conquerors, there are conquered, there are first comers, there are last comers
然後有征服者、被征服者、有先來者、有後到者
If you belong to such a society, the history you believe in is that kind of heroic history
你如果是這樣子的社會的話你相信的歷史就是那種英雄歷史
So you can see that all our complex societies, our so-called civilized societies have a history like this
所以大家看我們所有的複雜社會我們所謂的文明社會都是這樣子的歷史
Right? That history creates first comers and latecomers
對不對?那個歷史都會創造先來者、後道者
Whether it's American history or Taiwanese history, it's the same
不管是美國歷史或台灣歷史都一樣
The history of the South is the same
南國歷史都一樣
But this is the history of the gunman, the brother and ancestor on the other side of the gun
但是這個就是槍卒的、槍槍那邊的那個弟兄祖先的那種歷史
give us a great inspiration
就給我們一個很大的啟發
That is to say, human society can be like this
就是說原來人類的社會可以這樣子的
If you believe simple history like that
你如果相信那樣子簡單的歷史的話
In real people, it is
在現實的人群裡面就是
No first comer, no latecomer, no ruler, no ruled
沒有先來、沒有後道者、沒有統治者、沒有被統治者
right?
對不對?
Because that history is that simple
因為那個歷史就是那麼簡單
So if this is about the development of a human society
所以這個如果講到一個人類社會的發展
Actually, a subject that I am very interested in now
其實我現在非常感興趣的一個主題
I also hope that sometimes if young scholars in the social sciences or history
我也希望在座有時候如果讀社會科學或歷史學的年輕學者
Maybe this problem is not something I can solve
這個問題也許不是我能夠解決
Maybe it can be solved in your time
也許在你們那時候可以解決
because it's a big problem
因為這是一個很大的問題
Is human society the earliest
就是人類社會是不是最早
It is in a society that is planned one by one like the history of brothers and ancestors
就是在一個一個像弟兄祖先歷史所規劃的那種社會
fight each other in the area
在區域裡面互相鬥爭
right
對不對
dare not go out
不敢往外走
Since when did humans develop into a complex society
從什麼時候人類開始發展成一種複雜社會
when did it start
從什麼時候開始呢
Humans are brave enough to go out
人類很勇敢地走出去
by blood memory
靠著一種血緣記憶
You can find people of the same race to help you in far away places
可以在很遠的地方都可以找到同族的人幫忙
that i think
那這個我覺得
Do you feel that in-depth research
你覺得在深入的研究
This kind of Yizu
這個宜族的這種
This comparison between them and guns
這種他們跟仗槍之間的比較
maybe a clue
也許是一個線索
When explaining the Lord first
先早說明主的時候
stuck in 1950
卡在1950
in the 1960s
1960年代的時候
It seems that after the founding of the Communist Party of China
好像中共建政之後
as if there was a break
就好像有一個斷
Then I thought of my two or three brothers who had studied with Mr. Liu Shaohua before.
那我就想到好像之前有讀過劉少華老師的我的兩三兄弟
He also talks about the two-three-one family
他也是講兩三一族
He said that after the 1950s and 1960s, the two or three ones
他說兩三一族到五零六零年代之後
It seems to be the very traditional habit that is traditional in the mountains now
好像是現在傳統在山裡面的那種很傳統的習性
These changes by modernity or total regime
受到現代性或者總共政權的這些改變
will affect his old tradition and model
會去影響到他舊有的一個傳統和模式
The teacher's story just now actually stopped at a specific number of years
那老師剛剛的故事其實有停頓在一個特定的年限
I want to know what happened after that
那想知道那後來之後發生了什麼事情
Or what the teacher just said
或者說老師剛剛講的這些
Does the process of the speech just now still exist?
剛剛演講的那個過程還存在嗎
If it does not exist, it is now newly created some memories of his family to change
那如果不存在的話是現在新造成了他家之的一些記憶去改變
Or is it a very formal regime to influence
還是說是一個很腔式的一個政權去影響到
Then this is the so-called teacher
那這是所謂的老師的那個什麼
situational structure
情境結構所謂的
and then go on to something that has a realistic structure
然後一直講到有一個現實結構的東西
ok , ok , that ' s a good question
OK,好,這是很好的問題
Let me say it again, that is to say, there are indeed some changes in the structure of reality now
我再講,就是說,的確現在有一些現實結構改變了
So, I say that culture is actually an appearance
所以,我講文化其實是一種表象
There is a change in that appearance
那個表象有一個改變
In fact, a simple example
其實講一個最簡單的例子
That is to say, the worship of the three gods of the gun bamboo we just talked about
就是說,我們剛才講的槍竹的那種三神崇拜
right?
對不對?
What about now, because their country
那現在呢,因為他們國家呢
Especially after the 2008 earthquake
尤其在2008大地震之後
Bring down all the spears and bamboos on many mountains
把很多山上的槍竹全部牽到底下來
So its traditional fields are useless
所以它傳統的那些領域就沒有用了
But, there's another big support competition
但是呢,另外又有一個很大的支援競爭
It is from the grass, from me, everyone knows that the east from the grass
就是從草,從我,大家知道東從下草
From the time when I first went to Gunzhu to do field work
從我最早到槍竹那邊做田野的時候
Two yuan a piece, now forty-five to fifty yuan a piece
兩塊錢一根,到現在四十五到五十塊錢一根
From the price of grass so high
從草的價格這麼高
Who cares about those boundaries on the hill?
誰會在乎山上的那些界限?
right? and then everybody's pushing that line
對不對?然後大家都在突破那個界限
Then everyone will stop worshiping the Three Gods
那麼大家就不拜三神了
it is very simple
這是很簡單
That is to say, the support boundary between the human beings represented by the three gods
就是說那種三神他所代表的人類之間的支援界限
This has all been changed
這種都被改變了
Then this worship of the three gods is no longer remembered.
那麼這個三神崇拜也沒有再記了
But there are some social realities that still exist
但是有一些社會現實還是存在的
For example, I thought it was funny when I was doing fields over there
譬如說我在那邊做田野的地方就覺得很好笑
It's from Liang Shanzhou and Ababa Zhou.
就是梁山舟跟阿爸舟這邊的
Some of the behaviors of some local cadres I have seen are different
一些我看了一些地方幹部的作為不一樣
The local cadres on the Abazhou side are often people who take care of their hometown
阿爸舟這邊的地方幹部常常都是照顧本鄉的人
The local cadres on Liang Shanzhou's side are all from the same family.
梁山舟那邊的地方幹部照顧都是本家之的人
One is a society that pays attention to space
一個是注重空間的一個社會
A society that values kinship
一個是注重血緣的社會
You see it's still like this
你看到了現在還是這個樣的
some things still haven't changed
有一些還是沒有變
But basically because the state's involvement is too deep now
但是基本上因為現在國家的介入太深了
This change is very big
這個改變是非常大的
but we have this
但是我們對這個
Let me give you another small example
我再舉一個很小的例子
you know we're going to reflect
你就知道我們要去反思
not necessarily in this
不一定在這種
Before the intervention of contemporary national and ethnic classifications
當代的國家、民族分類介入之前
It's like a utopia, it's not
那個是一個好像理想國並不是
That is to say, that kind of small village does not necessarily look like an ideal country in society.
就是說那種小村在社會不見得理想國
I once chatted with an old man who was fighting with guns
我有一次跟一個槍斗的老人在聊天
He told me about the past where they lived in fear of violence
他就跟我講過去他們生活在這種恐懼暴力
In this endless war between the village and the village
村在跟村在之間的這種無止期的戰爭裡面
Then he talked and finally he suddenly smiled wryly
然後他講了最後他突然苦笑一下
like self-deprecating
好像自我解嘲一樣
He said it was because we people in the past had no knowledge
他說那是因為我們過去的人沒知識
Didn't know we were one nation
不知道我們是一個民族
So what I heard at that time was
所以我那個時候聽到就是
shouting hairs stand on end
喊毛都豎起來
why?
為什麼呢?
as if we were deconstructing this knowledge system
好像我們是在解構這個知識系統
Right? A lot of our research is deconstructing this knowledge system
對不對?我們很多的研究是在解構這個知識系統
deconstructing the national identity
在解構這個民族認同
Why do we do this?
我們為什麼要這樣做?
right?
對不對?
In fact, why did I emphasize a kind of reflective identification later on?
其實我後來為什麼我強調的一種反思性認同
that is
就是說
You still agree that you are a gunman
你還是認同你是槍卒
You still agree that you are a Mongolian pawn
你還是認同你是蒙古卒
but
但是呢
I don't necessarily have to accept what you say
我不一定要接受你說的那種
The history of my mainline defeating your mainline
我的主線打敗你的主線那種歷史
it means i have a new way of thinking about history
就是說我對歷史有一種新的想法
under this idea
在這種想法之下
i admit i am a gunman
我承認我是槍卒
I admit that I am a Mongolian soldier
我承認我是蒙古卒
right
對
that for what you just said
那個針對你剛剛講的
i have a bit of that what
我有一點那個什麼
Carmen
Carmen
you just mentioned
你剛剛提到說
There is a place where there are those brothers
有個地方有那個幾個兄弟
Their history is different
他們講的歷史都不太一樣
right
對不對
Then I'm thinking that his brother may not be the brother on the snowman
那我在想他這個兄弟可能不是雪人上的兄弟
or that is to say
還是就是說
Didn't you just say that?
你剛剛不是講嗎
That is to say, after he signed
就是說他簽署以後
Then his kinship is all over again.
那麼他的親戚關係就又重新發生了
It is possible that it was signed by a different place.
那有可能那是不同地方簽過去的
That's called brother
那雖然稱為兄弟
But it's not actually the student's brother
但其實並不是學員上的兄弟
So they will have different histories
所以他們會有不同的歷史
Maybe it's because of this
有可能是因為這樣子
This is a
這是一個
Then again, you just mentioned
然後再來就是說你剛提到說
have a nation
有個民族
He memorized the long, long history of this main line
他給記那個很長很長的這個主線歷史
right
對不對
You remind me of that America
你這個就讓我想起那個美國
There used to be a book called Healing, right?
以前有本書叫跟對不對
He remembers the black man
他就記那個黑人
has been swinging his long, long history
一直從揮出他那個很長很長的歷史
That is to say, this thing is very similar to
就是說這個東西很像
That may mean that some ethnic groups
那可能就是說有某些民族
he is very
他就很
this is good at
這個擅長
Just remember this long, long history
就記這種很長很長的歷史
This is my second point
這是我的第二點
Then again, that is
那另外再來就是說
you just mentioned this confirmation
你剛提到這個證實
I actually hid the one in Zhongan Jie
我事實上偽藏上中安界那個
The one in the ancient book in Zhonganjie
中安界那個古籍的那個
so we see confirmation
我們這樣就看到證實
I found out that it is the proof of China
我發現就是中國那個證實
he is actually
他事實上是
that first step
那個第一步
we are talking now
我們現在講
It is a history written independently by the writer himself.
他是比較屬於寫者自己獨立寫的一個歷史
written from the writer's point of view
從寫者的觀念寫的
History of Mathematics from Chinese
從漢數學的歷史
Basically he is from the perspective of the royal family
基本上他都是站在皇室的角度
rewrite history
再寫歷史
So in Chinese political history
所以在中國的政史裡面
In fact there is a prejudice
事實上都有一個偏見
These emperors of China are all placed in this season
中國這些皇帝都放在本季裡面
In Chinese history, there is a calendar behind him
中國歷史裡面他後面都有那個歷算
He put the surrounding countries in the calendar
他把周邊的國家都放在歷算裡面
Calendar is to put together with ordinary famous people
歷算就是跟一般有名的人放在一起
he does not have an equal status
他並沒有一種平等地位
to treat other surrounding countries
去對待其他周邊的國家
I think like the CCP now
我認為像現在中共
He will not let the president of Taiwan
他不會讓台灣的總統
Go to an international conference and show up together
去參加國際會議一起出現
This mentality is the same as that written in history
這種心態跟歷史上寫的
The policy mentality is the same
政策這種心態是一樣的
right
對不對
He finally said that I am the country
他終於說我才是國家
then you are not a country
那你不是國家
we two leaders cannot sit together
我們兩個領導人不能坐在一起
just the same
就同樣的
So I think our Taiwan
所以我覺得我們台灣
can actually do one thing
實際上可以做一件事
That is to say, from the perspective of the common people and the people
就是說從老百姓跟人民的角度
to rewrite history
來重新寫歷史
including Chinese history
包括中國的歷史
Japanese history
日本歷史
korean history
韓國歷史
And the history of Southeast Asian countries
還有東南亞國家的歷史
then come on again
然後再來就是說
Inside our wicked traffic room
我們邪惡的交通室裡面
we are now in fact
我們現在事實上
There are very few exchanges with countries in Southeast Asia
對東南亞的國家的交流非常少
should be in high school
應該在高中裡面
The history of these Southeast Asian countries should be handed over
應該去交這些東南亞國家的歷史
We now have a close relationship with this country
我們現在跟這國的關係密切
There are many foreign brides
有很多外籍新娘
and foreign workers
還有外勞
But we know very little about them
但是我們對他們了解非常有限
So we should use the new angle
所以我們應該用新的角度
to rethink historical transactions
來重新思考歷史交易
i think i simply answer
我想我簡單回答
Your two previous questions are all right
你前面的兩個問題好了
first bro host stuff
第一個 兄弟主持人的東西
that's just a historical memory
那只是一種歷史記憶
that doesn't mean that means
那並不表示就是說
really some kind of blood relationship
真的有一些什麼血緣關係
That has nothing to do with real history
那個跟真實的歷史並沒有關係
But that doesn't mean he's not real
但是這並不表示他不真實
Which means it doesn't matter if it's real or not.
就是說那個是不是真實並不重要
What matters is how you narrate history
重要的是在於你怎麼樣去敘述歷史
Actually they are telling us
其實他們在跟我們講
when his family history
他家庭的歷史的時候
I have noticed my friend of Aiqigou
我都注意到我的那個愛奇溝的朋友
very interesting
都講得很有意思
he just said
他就說
How is my waist bully with his second brother and eldest brother?
我的腰霸跟他的二哥、大哥怎麼樣怎麼樣
Or what about my grandfather and his elder brother and second brother
或者說我的祖父跟他的大哥、二哥怎麼樣
the one he told us about
他跟我們所講的那個
It's about my grandfather's generation.
就是講我的祖父那一代
Let's talk about our father's generation
後講我們父親那一代
that statement is different
那個說法都不一樣
We all start with a grandfather
我們都是從個祖父開始說
My grandfather had two sons or something
我祖父有生了兩個兒子什麼什麼這樣的
they are not
他們不是
He is just parallel to start like this
他是就是平行的這樣開始
Then I noticed those
然後我注意到那些
that is to say it is a memory
就是說這是一種記憶
That means you can't think that
就是說你不能去認為那個
a patterned memory
這些一種模式化的記憶
like this one of the earliest
像這個最早的一些
In Tubo's document "Historical Collection of Han and Tibetan"
土波的文書《漢藏史集》裡面
He went to record some of China's
他去記載中國的一些
The history of the Tang Dynasty
唐代的歷史的時候
He also said that a certain emperor in the Tang Dynasty
他還說唐代某某皇帝
It's the oldest of his brothers
是他的幾個兄弟裡面的老幾
We saw this and thought it was weird
我們看了這個就覺得很奇怪
Because Chinese literature does not record in this way
因為中國文獻不會這樣記載
right
對不對
He still uses this narrative
他還是用這種敘述方式
what you just said
那你剛剛講的那個
That is to say, some are not of a certain nationality
就是說有的不是某一個民族
Especially good at recording relatively long histories
特別擅長於記載比較長的歷史
I think this is human ecology
這個我是覺得還是人類生態
in a human ecology
在某一種人類生態上
Some people need to memorize a longer history
某一些人他需要去記比較長的歷史
OK
OK
Professor Wei, may I ask?
唯教授我可以問嗎
Thanks
謝謝
I have three questions to ask
我有三個問題想請教
In the early 1980s, it happened that the two sides of the Taiwan Strait
在八十年初那時候剛好兩岸
After the tee you have studied in the past
三通以後您過去研究了
Yours has been there for ten years
您的這種在那裡待了十年
How to apply for the source of funding
經費的來源是怎麼樣申請到
the second one is
那第二個是
How do they see us Taiwanese
他們怎麼看到我們台灣人
Do they treat us as Han Chinese or
是把我們當作漢人還是
still fled
還是逃亡過去的
political group
的政治團體
How did you see this scholar from Taiwan?
那怎麼看到我們台灣來的這位學者
Will there be this feeling of being neglected?
會不會有這種被虧視的感覺
the third one is
那第三個是
because they you just mentioned they are
因為他們你剛剛有提到他們是
territorial idea of border
邊界的領地觀念
Then they were in the previous life
那麼他們在前一世
For the current new ruler in group affairs
群事裡面對於現在新的統治者
It's the Chinese Communist Party
就是中共他們
after unification
統一之後
for this
對於這種
new leader new
新的領導新的
political interference
政治的干涉
their hearts are repulsive or
他們的內心是排斥的或者是
like you just mentioned
像你剛剛提到的
They try to accept him
他們就想辦法去接受他
I have these three questions
我有這三個問題
ok seems
ok 好像
The first question is funding
第一個問題經費問題
I can tell you it's expensive
我可以跟你說很花錢
What about the moving fields?
移動的田野呢
What about a squatting field?
跟一個蹲點的田野呢
not the same
不太一樣
that means you're going a lot
就是說你要去很多
Then you have to go to a different place each time
然後你要每次要去不同的地方
Then I'm just like everyone
那我就是跟大家一樣
This National Science Council talks about the International Economic Council
這個國科會講進國際經會
we are willing to spend
我們願意去經費
All kinds of things you have to find a way to put into your brain
各種你就要想辦法繳進腦汁
find your funding
去找你的經費
That is to say, this kind of mobile field is indeed more expensive
就是說這種移動的田野的確是比較花錢
the second
第二個
that about you means i'm here
那關於你是說我在這邊
they look at my question
他們看我的這個問題
words to the gun column
對槍柱來講的話
They're all pretty cute
他們導致都蠻可愛的
That is to say, they think Taiwanese are Han Chinese.
就是說他們認為台灣人就是漢人
You are just like all Han people in mainland China
你就是跟所有的大陸的漢人一樣
Instead, it means I'm over there
反而就是說我在那邊
I give a very small example
我舉一個很小的例子
I speak Sichuan dialect to them all over there
我在那邊都跟他們講四川話
because they shot
因為他們槍柱
Because the language of each place is very different
因為每一個地方的語言差別很大
So they are together in Sichuan dialect
所以他們在一起四川話
but the most convenient
反而最方便
I also use Sichuan dialect for the interview
我採訪也是用四川話
I talked to him for a long time
我跟他講了很久
The last time a friend of mine was laughing next to Gunzhu's
最後有一次我一個朋友在旁邊笑槍柱的
asked an old lady
問了一個老太太
Said that Professor Wang came from Taiwan
說這個王教授在台灣來的
tell you
跟你講
Sichuan dialect, why don't you find it strange?
四川話,你怎麼不覺得奇怪?
The old lady said, is he Han Chinese? Of course I want to speak Chinese
老太太說,他是漢人嗎?當然想漢話
Because Sichuanese they speak Chinese, but he is Han
因為四川話他們是講漢話,但是他是漢人
Of course I think there is something strange about Chinese
當然想漢話有什麼稀奇
So I don't have that problem
所以我沒有那個問題
And of course when I was doing fieldwork over there
當然還有就是我在那邊做田野的時候
I do not engage with all academic institutions, localities, governments
我不跟所有的學術機構、地方、政府接觸
So let me teach you a wonderful feeling
所以我教大家一個妙覺
I was probably lucky, I didn't arrange it on purpose
我是大概是運氣好,不是我故意安排的
I first met a group of local model school teachers
我首先就是認識一批當地的示範學校的老師
Their students are scattered in all the township primary schools
他們的學生是分散在所有的鄉小
So every time they take me to the countryside
所以他們每一次帶我下鄉的時候
It's the teacher's teacher who brought his friend
是老師的老師帶他的朋友來
So my identity is very much helped by everyone
所以我的身份是非常受到大家幫助的
so what's your last question?
那你最後一個問題是什麼?
to the ethnic minorities in mainland China
對中國大陸的少數民族的
That gunman is a very special
那槍卒是一個很特別的
i can say this
我可以這樣講
That is to say, because they are caught between Han and Tibetan
就是說他們因為夾在漢藏之間
Then he is not a nation
然後他原來又不是一個民族
He is a crowd of many small places
他是很多的小地方的人群
In this way, when identifying and classifying
這樣子被在識別分類的時候
turned him into a pawn
把他變成槍卒的
So but the history of the Gunners is very important
所以但是槍卒的歷史倒是非常重要
Because from the historical memory of China
因為從中國的歷史記憶裡面
It seems that some historians think
好像有一些歷史學家認為
It seems that part of him has become the current Han Chinese
好像他有一部分變成了現在的漢人
Some of them became the present Tibetans
有一部分變成了現在的藏族
so this is very interesting
所以這就是非常有意思
That is to say, if you believe in that history
就是說你如果相信那個歷史的話
Then the gunmen are there again
然後槍卒又存在在那裡
The existence of the gunman
那個槍卒的存在
It seems to prove that history exists
好像就證明那個歷史存在
everyone knows what it means
大家知道這個意思
so why would there be
所以為什麼會有
A group as small as 300,000
30萬那麼小的一個族群
become a very important nation
變成一個很重要的民族
Because he proves that Han and Tibetan belong to one family
因為他證明漢藏是一家的
But for gunmen
但是對於槍卒來講
they are also proud
他們也很驕傲
this is the gun column
是這樣子的槍柱
Of course he doesn't know the historical construction behind it
當然他不知道背後的歷史的建構
what those
什麼那些的
All he knows is that they are now one
他只知道他們現在變成一個
The gun column under the great history
很偉大的歷史底下的槍柱
And I get another from a myth
還有我再從一個神話
you can tell
你就可以看得出來
they often talk
他們常常講說
Guangong is your ancestor
官公是你們的祖先
your god
你們的神
Zhou Chang is our ancestor
周昌是我們的祖先
our god
我們的神
So he has a lot of local myths and legends
所以他有很多的當地的神話傳說
They all tell the story of Zhou Chang and the official
都講周昌跟官公的故事
In fact, there is a myth
其實其中有一個神話
That is to say, Zhou Chang thinks
就是說周昌認為
There are more and more Han Chinese here
這邊的漢人越來越多
feel bored
覺得滿煩的
He wants to carry a big rock
他就想背一個大石頭
shut the gate
把燕門關塞住
Don't let the Han people in
不讓漢人進來
He turned out to be a ghost
結果他是一個陰神
great strength
力氣很大
no mind
沒什麼頭腦
and only at night
而且只能在晚上活動
So when he was carrying a big rock
所以他背著大石頭的時候
that official is very cunning
那個官公很狡猾
Basic Education for Officials and Officials
官公就學基教
Zhou Chang just threw the stone and ran away
周昌就把石頭一丟就跑掉了
So now the Han people are still here
所以現在這邊漢人還在
that's all
就是這麼多
So what I mean by this joke is that
所以我講這個笑話的意思就是說
even if it's a joke
即使是一個笑話
even a myth
即使是一個神話
his appearance
他這些表象
There is an image behind him
他背後有個本象
The original image is the expression of their feelings
那個本象就是流露了他們那種感情
he still feels
他還是覺得
as if he accepts himself on the one hand
好像他一方面接受自己
The edge given to him by the Han
漢人給他的這種邊緣
image of minorities
少數民族的形象
Strong and brainless
有力氣沒頭腦
On the one hand, he thinks that the Han people are cunning
在一方面他又認為漢人是狡猾的
We can't beat the Chinese
我們鬥不過漢人
so we have to be like this
所以我們都要這樣子
But from other myths
但從別的神話裡面
he told me again
他又跟我講
he said look
他說你看
That Zhou Chang of yours is holding a Daguan knife
你們那個周昌拿著大關刀
Why did he choose Zhou Chang?
他為什麼選周昌
is very meaningful
是很有意義的
Zhou Chang is holding a Daguan knife
周昌拿著大關刀
standing behind the Han
站在漢人的身後
he means
他的意思是說
He said you Chinese
他說你們漢人
We are standing with the Han people
我們是跟漢人站在一起的
We are different from those Western Fans
我們跟那些西藩不一樣
That Xi Fan is independent
那個西藩是搞獨立的
Xifan refers to the Tibetan
西藩是指藏族
Because they often hear Tibetans seeking independence
因為他們常常聽到藏族的搞獨立
so at this time
所以在這個時候
He has
他有
He wants to choose a side, he is sandwiched between Han and Tibetan
他要選邊站 他夾在漢藏之間
So he chose to go out of state
所以他選擇出州
We are standing with the Han people
我們是跟漢人站在一起的
then speak more exaggeratedly
然後講得更誇張一點
You see, you Han officials still need our protection
你看 你們漢人官公還需要我們保護
We stand behind him with big knives
我們拿著大刀 站在他後面
So you from these myths and legends
所以你從這些神話傳說
or some popular local images
或當地流行的一些圖像
In fact, they are all signs
其實都是表徵
Regardless of the history I just analyzed earlier
不管是我剛剛前面分析的那些歷史
These myths and legends that I am telling now
跟我現在所講的這些神話傳說
or images are actually the same
或圖像 其實都一樣
what i promote
我所推廣的
Then what I want to advocate is
後來我想提倡的就是
How do we learn from these representational phenomena
我們怎麼樣從這些表徵的現象
Inside to see the real side
裡面去看真實的邊相
return some of the emotions in it
還人在其中的一些情感
Hello Mr. Wang
王老師您好
my question is
我的問題是
China was a unified country during the Qin and Han Dynasties
中國在秦漢時期是一個統一的國家
Then the Western Roman Empire
然後西方的羅馬帝國時期
It is also a unified empire
也是一個統一的一個大帝國
Well, after China's continuous division
那麼中國在不斷地分裂之後
It will also revert to the situation where the unity
它還會恢復到統一的那種情況
But after the division of the West, it became countless small countries
但是西方在分裂之后就变成了无数的小国家
This phenomenon is caused by the use of
因为是使用的原因造成了这种现象
Apart from geographical factors
抛除地理因素之外
this problem is too big
这个问题太大了
I really have no way to answer
我真的是没有办法回答
But I'm thinking of having a
不过我在想有一个
I think I think it's the same wherever I say it
我觉得我想我在哪里讲都是一样
This is what I said in mainland China and Taiwan
我在中国大陆在台湾讲的这样
From the point of view of human ecology
从人类生态的观点来讲
If you take the whole of Eurasia
你如果把整个欧亚大陆
cut in half
切成两半
Half of them are from China
有一半是中国这边
Emphasis on diversity
讲求多元一体
Put all Xinjiang and Tibet in one big China
把所有的新疆西藏都放在一个大中国里面
the other side is
另外有一边是
There are several very rich and powerful small countries along the coast
沿海有几个非常富强的小国家
in France, Germany, England, etc.
都在法国、德国、英国这些
Then the inland is often involved
然后内陆就经常卷入
In this chaos of ethnicity, gender, religion, etc.
族群、性别、宗教各种的这种分乱里面
Then everyone saw the recent large number of refugees
然后大家看到最近大批的难民
flee to the east
往這個東邊逃
If everyone was a scholar of modern history
如果當初大家是在近代史的學者
everybody knows
大家都知道
At that time Sun Yat-sen and many of these revolutionaries
當時孫中山和許多的這些革命
early revolution this home
早期的革命這個家
also advocates building a very small China
也主張建一個非常小的中國
And leave Mongolia, Tibet, and all Xinjiang outside
而把蒙古、西藏、所有新疆都拋在外面
If a China like this was established at that time
如果那個時候這樣子的中國建立起來的話
in that human ecology
在那種人類生態上
I think it's still the same today
我想今天還是一樣
Refugees are not only running to the west but also to the east
難民也不只往西邊跑也往東邊跑
So in terms of human ecology, I think the eastern half
所以人類生態上我覺得東半部
So far it looks like it's better than the western half
目前看起來好像是優於西半部
But overall
但是在整體來講
still too far away
還是差太遠
That is to say, the whole so-called pluralism issue in China
就是說中國整個所謂的多元議題
There are still many problems inside
內部還是有非常多的問題
to solve
要去代解決
Thanks
謝謝
Im honest, Im a student who has studied the Chinese language of the teacher in animals before.
老實好 我是以前有在動物修過老師的漢話論述的學生
The one who saw the teacher before
那 以前看老師的那個
At the edge of China, first recruit people from the teacher
華夏邊緣的時候 先向老師招人
The previous part is very incomprehensible
前面的部分非常的看不懂
But the more I read the teacher's book, the more interesting I find it.
可是老師的書 越看越覺得很有意思
Especially when the teacher talked about Taiwan in the last piece
尤其是老師最後一張講到台灣的部分的時候
The teacher mentioned in it
老師在裡面有提到
Because that book was written by the teacher at the end of the Twenty-Four Classics
因為那本書是老師二十四經末的時候寫的
Then it mentioned some of the status of Taiwan's aboriginal research at that time
然後有提到當時台灣的原住民研究的一些狀況
Especially in the past two years, it seems that it is more and more easy to see on the Internet that there is a saying
尤其是最近兩年好像網路上越來越容易看到有一種說法
Think that the vast majority of people in Taiwan are descendants of the poor
認為台灣的人絕大部分是貧普族的後代
In fact, I re-read the teacher's book recently, and I feel very emotional
其實最近又重看老師的書 感覺很有感受
Is there any way for many teachers to make some expansions for this place?
那不少的老師有沒有辦法針對這個地方做一些擴充
Thanks
謝謝
This is what happens all over the world
這個就是其實在全世界都有這樣的現象
I think everyone just often has some imagination
我覺得大家就是經常會有一些去想像
Imagine who our main thread is
想像我們的主線是誰
In fact, he is showing a reality
其實他表現的是一種現實
Sometimes we don't need to pay too much attention
有的時候我們不用去太注意
or to criticize the imagination
或者是批判那種想像
or constructed history
或者是被建構的歷史
I think what we should do instead
我覺得我們反而要做的
is to analyze this imagination
是分析這種想像
what is this emotion or intention behind it
它背後代表的這種情感或意圖是什麼
This time my answer to your question
這次我對你這個問題的回答
Well, today we are very, very grateful to Academician Wang
好 我們今天非常非常感謝王院士
give us such a wonderful speech
給我們這麼精彩的演講
Answered many, many questions
也答覆了非常非常多人的問題
Okay, thank you
好 謝謝
Falcon
Falcon